<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>La scala santa, or, A scale of devotions musical and gradual being descants on the fifteen Psalms of Degrees, in metre : with contemplations and collects upon them, in prose, 1670.</title>
            <author>Coleraine, Hugh Hare, Baron, 1606?-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97354</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5066</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12633503</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12633503</idno>
            <idno type="VID">199576</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97354)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199576)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 348:9 or 719:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>La scala santa, or, A scale of devotions musical and gradual being descants on the fifteen Psalms of Degrees, in metre : with contemplations and collects upon them, in prose, 1670.</title>
                  <author>Coleraine, Hugh Hare, Baron, 1606?-1667.</author>
                  <author>Loredano, Giovanni Francesco, 1607-1661. Gradi dell'anima. English.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 84 p. : ill., music  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Godbid and J. Playford,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Hugh Hare, Baron Coleraine, in NUC pre-1956  and Wing; Wing also enters this work under Giovanni Francesco Loredano.</note>
                  <note>The translation of Loredano's Gradi dell'anima appears on reel 719 only.</note>
                  <note>Errata on p. [17]</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>This item can also be found following "Ascents of the soul" at reel 719:18.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in Edinburgh University Library and Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Entry cancelled for L3069 in Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXX-CXXXIV --  Paraphrases, English.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXX-CXXXIV --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Psalms (Music)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:199576:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>the ASCENTS of the SOVL</head>
                  <p>ASSENTS</p>
                  <p>Psalmodia</p>
                  <figDesc>King David plays his harp before the altar of sacrifice, while angels ascend a stairway to heaven</figDesc>
                  <q>1 Chron 15. Cap.</q>
                  <q>Colloss. 3.16.17.</q>
                  <signed>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>monogram</figDesc>
                     </figure> Design.</signed>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199576:1"/>
            <p>LA SCALA SANTA: OR, A Scale of Devotions <hi>MUSICAL</hi> and <hi>GRADUAL:</hi> BEING DESCANTS ON THE <hi>Fifteen Pſalms of Degrees, <hi>IN METRE;</hi>
               </hi> With <hi>Contemplations</hi> and <hi>Collects</hi> upon them, <hi>IN PROSE,</hi> 1670.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Epictet. in Arrian. Diſſert. <hi>lib. 1. cap. 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Godbid</hi> and <hi>J. Playford,</hi> Anno Dom. 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:199576:2"/>
            <head>THE MIND OF THE FRONTISPIECE.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reatneſs and Piety combine</l>
            <l>To make the <hi>Pſalmodiſt</hi> Divine</l>
            <l>(Good Actions following pure Intents)</l>
            <l>His Soul ASCENDS, his God ASSENTS.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="ode">
            <pb facs="tcp:199576:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable THE LEARNED AUTHOR.</head>
            <head type="sub">A PINDARIQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E ODE.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ouze up dull Quill, and never Dormant lye</l>
               <l>Upon thy Cotton Pillow, ſtiff and dry;</l>
               <l>Uſeleſs, and void of all Activity.</l>
               <l>I'le not diſturb thy Reſt</l>
               <l>To travel long, in queſt</l>
               <l>Of ſome impertinent Romance,</l>
               <l>To Ape the fond or ſighing Lover:</l>
               <l>No, for by chance</l>
               <l>I lately did diſcover,</l>
               <l>In a fair view upon the Proſpect-Land,</l>
               <l>Greatneſs and Goodneſs walking hand in hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>By the ſafe Conduct of a gentle Muſe</l>
               <l>I trac'd a Royal Court,</l>
               <l>Which led me to the Sacred Fort,</l>
               <l>Where Strength and Beauty might amuſe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:199576:3"/>
               <l>Fifteen Aſcents of fair and precious Stone,</l>
               <l>(Not ſuch as here are found)</l>
               <l>Did mount me from the lower Ground,</l>
               <l>To view a large and wond'rous Throne;</l>
               <l>Whereon</l>
               <l>I ſpy'd a <hi>David,</hi> and a <hi>Jonathan.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>A <hi>Jonathan,</hi> who whilom did employ</l>
               <l>His Quill, to imp his Dart;</l>
               <l>Whereby not to annoy</l>
               <l>Young <hi>Jeſſe</hi>'s Heart:</l>
               <l>But Love, and needful Secrets to impart.</l>
               <l>One who is able to engage</l>
               <l>With the <hi>Goliahs</hi> of the Age:</l>
               <l>Thoſe Debauchees, who complement</l>
               <l>A Cloud; and labour to entice</l>
               <l>The very Principles of Vertue into Vice,</l>
               <l>With gaudy and prophane Embelliſhment.</l>
               <l>Now, for the wanton Fancy's ſake,</l>
               <l>Their Souls lye canker'd in the Ruſt</l>
               <l>Of Eaſe ill-manag'd; now they make</l>
               <l>Greatneſs a Pander unto Luſt.</l>
               <l>If ever Prophecy did nick the Times,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>David</hi> foreſaw their<note n="*" place="margin">Scurrilis Cant. de <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide</hi> &amp; <hi>Bath.</hi> non ita pridem compoſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Dytherambique</hi> Rhimes;</l>
               <l>For when he counts his Injuries and Wrongs,</l>
               <l>He adds,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.12.</note> 
                  <hi>On me the Drunkards make their Songs.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>Oft have I ſeen the Sun's declining Light</l>
               <l>Drowſily nod down to the Lap of Night;</l>
               <l>But when (next Morn) the Champion wakes,</l>
               <l>(For 'tis not long he Dreams)</l>
               <l>About the Globe's wide Liſts a gallant Ring he takes,</l>
               <l>(Brandiſhing his Lance of Beams:)</l>
               <l>And when he manages a well-dreſt Ray,</l>
               <l>The Night-Mare Sleep (as frighted) ſtarts away.</l>
               <l>Old Darkneſs is diſmounted by the brisk young Day:</l>
               <l>The World's call'd up again, and Men revive</l>
               <l>With a more ſtrong aſſurance that they live.</l>
               <l>Thus when the ſhades of Drollery poſſeſt</l>
               <l>The Seat, where Virgin Muſes once did reſt:</l>
               <l>When we deſpair'd that pious Lays,</l>
               <l>Or uſeful Rhimes ſhould e're more guild our Days;</l>
               <l>A Star ſtrangely propitious did appear,</l>
               <l>Darting its Splendors from the wiſe Men's Hemiſphere;</l>
               <l>They'd much of Goodneſs, much of heav'nly Grace,</l>
               <l>As far as that can mix with humane Race;</l>
               <l>And did portend the overthrow</l>
               <l>Of ſordid Wit, (if that be <hi>Wit</hi> that ſome call'd ſo.)</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:199576:3"/>
            <lg>
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Their low-born Muſe, arm'd with Poetic Rage,</l>
               <l>And Licenſe, baſely congeed to the Stage;</l>
               <l>They trod mean Paths, whoſe whole Deſign and Wit</l>
               <l>Could reach no farther than the Neighb'ring Pit.</l>
               <l>When as your tow'ring Soul,</l>
               <l>Leaving us beneath,</l>
               <l>All humane Paſſions doth controul,</l>
               <l>And mount into thoſe Regions, where</l>
               <l>Is nought but pure and ſubtle Air,</l>
               <l>Where common Mortals cannot breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>Go on, thou noble <hi>Hero,</hi> who doſt know</l>
               <l>The Paths of Honour, and of Vertue too;</l>
               <l>A Soul ſo Skilful! ſo inur'd to Good!</l>
               <l>Never proud <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Roman</hi> underſtood:</l>
               <l>They only built a gaudy Theater</l>
               <l>Sacred to Vertue; thou haſt rais'd thy ſelf to her:</l>
               <l>Such a clean Lodging ev'ry Soul may boaſt,</l>
               <l>Who bears the Temple of the Holy-Ghoſt.</l>
               <l>Others for Pomp or Safety may provide</l>
               <l>Againſt their fatal Day,</l>
               <l>A coſtly Dungeon, or a <hi>Memphian</hi> Pyramid</l>
               <l>(T' incloſe their Souls too with their mould'ring Clay;)</l>
               <l>While by the Virtue of thy ſacred Fire,</l>
               <l>(Decree'd not to expire)</l>
               <l>Your Honour ſhall (ſurviving Fame)</l>
               <l>Live in a heav'nly Cone of Flame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>When I peruſe the Comment, and the Text,</l>
               <l>Nothing I find ſo dubious, or perplext,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tin.</hi> 1.14.</note>By <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Fables, or Conceits of Men;</l>
               <l>But your unerring Pen</l>
               <l>Dictator doth Commence,</l>
               <l>And reconcile King <hi>David</hi>'s ſenſe,</l>
               <l>With ſuch Illuſtrations there,</l>
               <l>As if thou wert his Privy-Counſellor:</l>
               <l>Your Verſion modeſt, and yet faithful too,</l>
               <l>Shews what thou doſt, and able art to do.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>My Numbers muſt fall ſhort, of what is due</l>
               <l>To ſuch pure Zeal, and depth of Judgment too:</l>
               <l>Fifteen Degrees! Henceforth ſhall every Pſalm</l>
               <l>Boaſt, that it can</l>
               <l>Receive the Honour of thy skilful Name,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>THE CHIEF MUSICIAN.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then, Pardon Sir, if I aſpire</l>
               <l>To kiſs the loweſt Step of your advanced Quire.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:199576:4"/>
            <head>AD NOBILISSIMUM AUTHOREM.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">J</seg>Actitet immenſi <hi>Salomonem</hi> Machina Templi</l>
            <l>Structorem, Graduum te Chorus ipſe canit:</l>
            <l>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Stantia non pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant tecta probare Deos: Mart. utpote Chriſtus Templi Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidium prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſagivit.</note>Illius obruitur moles operoſa ruinâ,</l>
            <l>Vim fruſtra his infers Veſpaſiane, tuam.</l>
            <l>Ficta Poetarum torpeſcant Numina, quorum</l>
            <l>Gleba Sepulchralis Frigida Membra tegit:</l>
            <l>Muſarum Lymphis incaſsùm labra retingunt,</l>
            <l>Ni prunam Linguis praebeat Ara ſuis.</l>
            <l>Veſtris aſpirat caeptis Deus ille Deorum,</l>
            <l>Et ſic Divino jure Poeta cluis:</l>
            <l>Te merito canimus; aujus conſcendere Scalam</l>
            <l>Laurea ſubrepens ambitioſa cupit:</l>
            <l>Te miſeret Plantae; quoties tremebunda precatur</l>
            <l>Ut Paradiſiacis inſita, vivat, Agris.</l>
            <l>O Dilecte Deo! pergas tibi ut Orbis Honore</l>
            <l>Agnoſcat nullum, nec Pietate, parem:</l>
            <l>Oro, ut dignêris Triviae Tentamina Muſae</l>
            <l>Quâ placidâ ſemper Fronte videre ſoles:</l>
            <l>For ſitan inſolitum videar compingere Carmen;</l>
            <l>Scilicet appoſitè ſcribere cauſa vetat.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Honoris veſtri obſequio deditiſſimus,</hi> S. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:199576:4"/>
            <head>TO THE Moſt Illuſtrious And Sereneſt STELLA.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S ſoon as Nature had awaked my Duty in the tender of its Devotion to <hi>Lucinda,</hi> I was prompted by Juſtice, as well as Love, to lay my next Offering at Your Feet, becauſe I muſt avow to all the World, that nothing hath that Aſcendant over my Soul as Ye Two have, who make my Paſſions high, yet honeſt; Ye are Twin-Stars of the firſt Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude, ſo that I cannot ſhew Ye my Reſpects, without advancing my Religion, Your Piety encouraging that unto ſome nobler Effort, while it inſtructs theſe in the moſt decent and humble ways of ſubmitting my Deſires to Heaven's acceptance firſt, and then to Your Graces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> You know I never yet approach'd You but with a Prayer, or with Muſick, (admiring the Divinity which ſtill arrays Your Perſon;) the Imitation of your Holy and Harmonious Mind, I think, is Work for the moſt Excellent upon Earth, as the Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:199576:5"/>of it is my chiefeſt pleaſure, and hath been the cauſe of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing theſe the Eſſays of my younger time, (began about twenty years ago at my entrance into Your Service) when I aim'd at nothing but God's Grace, and Yours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> The intent of my firſt Affections would palliate their weaker Actings, ſince (as the ſtrength of Zeal may ſtill excuſe ſome Errors) the Daughter of <hi>Time</hi> is here with a Gift, though the Daughter of <hi>Tyre</hi> be not in her Robes: Here is no gentile Vanity, or curious Texture of Wit; no Colours of Rhetorick, nor modiſh Points of Courtſhip, to inveigle Your Opinion of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Yet, Madam, here is that, may well become Your Grace,</l>
               <l>The moſt Angelike Dreſs, in faſhion upon Earth;</l>
               <l>The way to pierce the Skies, with Oriſons and Praiſe;</l>
               <l>The way to paſs our Lives, in trueſt Eaſe, and Mirth.</l>
            </q>
            <p>I wiſh You like the making up of this Suit (as it is) with the truth of his Devotion and Service, who is ready to wait upon You (in his Holy-day habit) both to Your Cloſet, and to Our Church, as</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>MADAM, <hi>The humbleſt and faithfulleſt of your Miniſters.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:199576:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING with much admiration and delight been long converſant with the <hi>Pſalter,</hi> I find, as it is wiſely appointed for the firſt Book that we read or ſtudy, ſo it may fitly be uſed to the laſt minute of our Life and Breathing;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 23.46. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.6.</note> ſince our bleſſed Lord himſelf handed his Soul unto his Father in theſe words of the <hi>Pſalmiſt.</hi> And I never knew any condition, how ſad ſoever, that might not receive ſome Entertainment,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.16. 21.42. 27.46. 22.44. 13.35. <hi>John</hi> 2.17. 6.32. 10.34. 13.18. 15.25. 19.24.</note> ſome Company and Diſcourſe (as well as <hi>Muſic</hi>), and ſo ſome eaſe and relief from that glorious Book of the <hi>Pſalms;</hi> which is not only beautified by our Saviour his frequent uſe of it (both living and dying,) but by the continual Services, and beſt Devotion of all the Saints and Children of God: For (to ſay nothing of the Eſteem it hath, even in the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Religion) there hath been no Church, either of <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> nay, ſcarce one eminent Perſon in either of thoſe Churches,<note place="margin">Sixty Proofs cited out of the Pſalms in the <hi>N. T.</hi> Pſal. <hi>1.2.</hi>
               </note> who hath not only allowed much time and attention, but likewiſe ſhewn the greateſt remarks of Piety and Zeal, in the ſtudious peruſal thereof. For theſe Spiritual Songs (as all ſacred
<pb facs="tcp:199576:6"/>Worſhip was of old wrapt up in <hi>Metre</hi>) do, with their moſt charming Melody, and ſweetneſs of Expreſſion, both ſet forth the Law of the Lord, and the love of his Servants, (as on Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> not on <hi>Sinai, viz.</hi>) in ſo lofty and taking a way, as that ſurely they contain not only the Body and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but the Spirit and Quinteſcence, the pleaſant Taſts, and beſt Reliſhes of our holieſt Religion! Beſides the variety of Subjects, and richneſs of each Theme, ſerving (as the Treaſures of ſeveral Mines) for the furniſhing and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding both our fancies and labours with Materials, ſufficient to pleaſe, to profit, to enrich our Meditations. So that truly 'tis a raviſhing, and no leſs than Heavenly delight, to hear the holy Perſons of all Times and Ages (like Birds in the Spring) deſcanting on the ſelf-ſame Subject; but with ſuch different Notes, Melody, and Accent, as it is wonderful to obſerve (while every one doth well in doing his beſt,) what rare Diviſions are run by the joyning of ſo full a Conſort: Whilſt the Muſic becomes more excellent by the admirable variety thereof.</p>
            <p>This hath often ſet on work, and ſatisfied my Thoughts with the Contemplation of our Eternal employ, the praiſing of God in Heaven, perhaps too in the Songs of <hi>David,</hi> (as well as of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſince theſe were the Songs of the Lamb while he was here on <hi>Sion</hi>) according to our beſt Capacities and Viſions: So that as the Angels envy not the Cherub for ſitting higher, or ſeeing more than they; nor the Seraphim deſpiſe the Angels, becauſe theſe cannot reach the others Pitch in their mighty Raptures and heavenly Addreſſes, (for they are all in the ſame way, though concerned in ſeveral degrees of Duty;) It is my opinion, that no true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſhould be diſcouraged, either by his own weakneſs, or others greater Abilities, from turning <hi>Pſalmodiſt,</hi> and helping the Quire with his Notes, though they be of a harſher kind, and flatter Key, than many others which are uſed there; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe both in the Church here, and that above, he muſt ſing the ſame which others do, though (it may be) not with the ſame Elegance; yet if his Heart be right, and his Deſires ſincere, though his Place and Parts may be inferiour to many, his good Will and Intent ſhall afford joy, ſatisfaction, and bliſs, and ſecure him from the Cenſure of all others.</p>
            <p>Nay, he may ſuppoſe the Muſic and the Mirth of Saints to ariſe like the Flame from thoſe loweſt Coals of the Altar,
<pb facs="tcp:199576:6"/>which lie obſcurely in their Aſhes; and thence to aſcend by the Degrees of the Sons of Fire to the top of their lofty Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid, the <hi>Deity;</hi> and from that Central Point again ſtream forth ſuch Harmony and Delight, as may reach and fill, enflame and enlighten, array and gild the whole Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the Bleſt Eternity.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſince he which hath the loweſt Voice may bear a Part in Muſic, we ſhould neither contemn nor hinder their ſinging, who cannot reach ſo high a ſtrain as our ſelves; but bear with, or encourage, rather than ſilence and diſturb the Devotions of the weakeſt, who may be more acceptable to God in their well-meaning, than we are to Men in our finer expreſſions.</p>
            <p>Upon this account I have often judged it expedient, that Cenſure ſhould be ſhut out of the Church Doors, when any ones Verſe or Muſic is brought within them; and though we might be able to mend that which is there allowed, yet we are rather to uſe than blame it, becauſe it is preſcribed by ſuch, whom we muſt yield beſt able to diſcern what is fit for the public Worſhip, which certainly differs from each Man's private Devotions, more than doth his Night-dreſs from the Habit he muſt wear at Noon-day.</p>
            <p>So that though I might plead for <hi>Hopkin</hi>'s and <hi>Sternhold</hi>'s, for the meaneſt Tranſlation of the Pſalms in our Pariſh Churches, (as Men do for ſome Cuſtoms and Faſhions) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe countenanced by Authority and long Uſage; yet I would not from thence conclude, that they are the beſt, or that I muſt keep them in my own Cloſet, or particular Devotions: But as I will not refuſe them publicly whilſt commanded, ſo I will not reproach them privately; much leſs cenſure or deter others in their ſingular Induſtry, who have not only deſign'd, but attempted, both to do better than the weakeſt Age of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Poetry; and withall, equal the ſtrongeſt Reach of Sence and Expreſſion that is found in the beſt Tranſlators of the Pſalms.</p>
            <p>Amongſt whom I would count two very late Authors,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> S. W. <hi>Mr.</hi> M. S.</note> (who might be fancied the two Poles, including a World of our Rithmical Paraphraſts, and pretending ſomething above them) but that the one ſeems to be in the exceſs of Gaudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and liberty of Fancy, while the other is in the worſe extream of meanneſs of Verſe, and want of plainneſs; ſo that as the former will be thought by ſome too Luxuriant and
<pb facs="tcp:199576:7"/>Copious, (both in Meaſure and Conceit) the latter will be found incurious, and fallen ſhort of expectation; ſince he forgets the Poet, while he ſtoops to accommodate the People, and can neither afford Rhime to half his Lines, (which is eaſie enough to be had in our tinkling Tongue) nor clearneſs to his Verſe, which might have excuſed the other defect, (and is but needful for the vulgar way of reading, and then ſinging) becauſe the Sentence of his Verſe too frequently out-runs the Meaſures, and ſo leaves that unfiniſhed at the end of theſe; which ſurely is a fault that my ſelf (as moſt others) may be guilty of ſometimes in thoſe ſhort <hi>Caeſura's</hi> we make uſe of, but ſhould be avoided with all poſſible care; for when the Stops reach farther than the Lines, the Breaks of theſe muſt needs be as unpleaſant to the Ear, as it is commonly in jurious to the Sence: And ſo are the big-belly'd <hi>Epithetes</hi> (the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) wherewith ſome Verſions abound, which are <hi>Pedantic</hi> Charms, conjuring Ignorance into Admiration, pleaſing or employing thoſe moſt of all, who leaſt underſtand their uſe and meaning: Whereas the words of Truth and Soberneſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 26.25. <hi>Gen.</hi> 34. <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.14.</note> ſuch as were dictated by God's own Spirit, want (no Bombaſt) neither the <hi>Dreſs</hi> of <hi>Dinah,</hi> nor of <hi>Thamar,</hi> to make them ſeem <hi>wanton,</hi> and then <hi>alluring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Heathens</hi> indeed ſet out their Fables, like Proſtitutes, to put them off, and made them cried up by the miſtakes of too many; but to trick up the moſt Sacred Poems in the mode of the Idolatrous <hi>Ethnick,</hi> is a Licenſe no Man hath a Patent for from Holy Writ: And though, with <hi>Politian</hi> and <hi>Bonamy,</hi> ſome have preferred <hi>Pindar,</hi> I think there are as many genuine Beauties, excellent Parts and Proportions in <hi>David,</hi> as in any uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtine,</hi> any monſtrous <hi>Pagan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.12.</note> we can meet with: And as he appeared to <hi>Samuel,</hi> when God himſelf ſaid, <hi>Ariſe, anoint him, for this is he;</hi> ſo when I look upon him in his Pſalms, I gueſs ſurely the <hi>Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lord</hi> is before me. How frequent, full, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, are his Metaphors, Similies, Figures, and Enrichments of Phraſe! All which ought to have right done them, (being the <hi>Daughters</hi> to ſo great a King) and to be cloathed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Quality and Excellency;<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.34.</note> and that is not with <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Garments, with the Thread of <hi>Egypt,</hi> or the Garb of Aliens, but, like the Silk-worm, only with Robes ſpun out of their own Bowels; for they are rich enough to furniſh
<pb facs="tcp:199576:7"/>themſelves (as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did their Tabernable) both with Coverings and Ornaments: And as the Armour of <hi>Saul</hi> did not fit <hi>David</hi>'s Perſon, no more doth extravagant Words or Conceits become his Poems,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.18.</note> who is ſaid to be as <hi>prudent</hi> in his Speech, as <hi>skilful</hi> in his Muſic.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing there are ſuch appoſite Alluſions and Relations in each part of theſe Divine Poems to the other Portions of holy Writ, which (as the Rays of the Sun do to the World) dart Light and Beauty from one corner of the Bible to the other; we need repair to no other Wardrobe than the Book of God, for the trimming out any part of it, with ſufficient elegancy, fulneſs, and embelliſhment.</p>
            <p>Therefore I endeavour in theſe Eſſays, not only to have as much of the ſence of the Pſalm, but likewiſe of ſuch other Scriptures as it may ſeem to relate to, (whereby it may be unfolded and adorned) that they might be compoſed in the plaineſt <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and eaſieſt manner of Verſe; yet with as much of holy Writ as can be put into them, ſtudying for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity between them and the Original, more than Curioſity in the Texture; and to be full, though not prolix; and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to ſome, if not pleaſant.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Hillary</hi> ſhews us from the <hi>Revelations</hi> who it is that holds the Key of <hi>David:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.7.</note> It is too hard for any Mortal to open the Door of this vaſt Palace. Humane Fancy may peep in, only to ſee it, might go far, rather than venture therein to loſe it ſelf. And if the adventurous Poet draw <hi>Stanza's</hi> of an extraordinary length (like a Body on the Wrack) the Coherence of the Parts is often looſen'd, diſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or undiſcerned; and the Muſician diſcouraged from ſetting or compoſing ſuch tedious Numbers into Anthems, ſince theſe are uſually not long.</p>
            <p>And if it be ſo, (as I have heard) that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Meter through the Book of <hi>Pſalms</hi> is generally very ſhort, ſurely we are more obliged to conform to the Original, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our Feet (as near as may be) by that Model, or elſe by the Standard Meaſures of our Age, which have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, known, and directed, even to the vulgar: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as I have ſomewhat obſerved the manner of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Muſic in theſe <hi>Pſalms of Degrees,</hi> (by frequent Repetitions and Reſponſes) ſo I have confined my ſelf, perhaps with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out too much ſtraitneſs, to the Staffs, our ordinary Church Tunes do lean upon, that they may be made uſeful to many
<pb facs="tcp:199576:8"/>by the common Notes, as they may become grateful to others by their being capable of various better Compoſitions, (they being deſigned for Anthems and Hymns, as well as Pſalms.)</p>
            <p>Yet would I not have them humorouſly ſet up, nor ſent forth ſtrangely dreſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 17.5. 19.29.</note> like the <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> of the <hi>Levite,</hi> or the <hi>Idol</hi> of the <hi>young Man;</hi> but modeſtly and gravely accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred like the <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.</note> like our Church of <hi>England,</hi> that the Graces in theſe Spiritual Songs may be more char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, as more conſpicuous, by being ſuited to the benefit and converſation of all, even of the loweſt, as well as of the ſublimer Capacities: Since by theſe I wiſh as general a good as is poſſible, without any undeſerved Praiſe to my ſelf, or any Detraction from another Perſon. For though I have pointed a two modern Men, as the <hi>Herculean</hi> Pillars, between whom I take my way; yet I have no great occaſion to find fault with them, becauſe the one ſtands on this ſide, and the other on that, of the Courſe I ſteer, whilſt both ſerve to my ſafer Convoy into thoſe <hi>Streights</hi> whither I am bound.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the kinds of Verſe I make uſe of, are neither grateful nor faſhionable (in this Licentious and <hi>Dyther ambique</hi> Time); but they are the beſt known of any, and have no ſmall intereſt in the common Approbation; and, as the old Maxim told me, <hi>The more common the better,</hi> of what is good: So the late excellent Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> (Dr. <hi>H. King</hi>) indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced me, rather (by his Example) to redreſs and amend the Vulgar, than to deride their lame and feeble Sence; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if (by the boldeſt attempts of Wit and Learning) we cannot come near the Majeſty and Excellency of the firſt Pen-man, it is more reaſonable that we ſhould ſubmit our Endeavours (as <hi>Publicola</hi> did his Faſces) to the uſe and benefit of the moſt and meaneſt, rather than make them Trophies of our own Arrogance, and our Brethren's weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Our continual work is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 9.49, 50.</note> to have about us that <hi>Salt</hi> of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> which may <hi>ſeaſon</hi> our Offerings both to God and Man, while we thank the one, or aſſiſt the other.</p>
            <p>Is it not double Superſtition, and worſe than Folly, to court the Prayers of Men in Heaven, and the Praiſes of Men on Earth? 'Tis enough to have an Intereſt quite other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Religion, and to forward Man's Good with God's Glory, (more than with our own); or God's Bleſſing with our own good Deeds, rather than with others good Words.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199576:8"/>
            <p>So that I would not be thought Cenſorious nor Singular, nor any other ways <hi>Phariſaical</hi> in my Entertainments here. Though I bring ſeveral Courſes of Devotion, they are not worthy to be compared to the good piece of Fleſh, and Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon of Wine, wherewith our great Exemplar once treated the People; yet (let theſe be never ſuch courſe Fare) they are really deſigned for a Bleſſing to all, as <hi>David</hi>'s Banquet was, in 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.34. and I can conclude with his Royal word, <hi>As for me,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 29.17, 18.</note> in the uprightneſs of my Heart I have willingly offered all theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Noli altum ſapere, ſed time.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:199576:9"/>
            <head>More ERRATA's in the Firſt Part.</head>
            <p>PAg. 11. l. 34. <hi>read</hi> off. l. 42. <hi>r.</hi> holieſt. p. 14. l. 3. <hi>inſert</hi> thou. p. 15. l. 30. <hi>inſert</hi> is the wickedneſs of Folly, Eccleſ. 7.25. l. 41. <hi>dele</hi> from. p. 16. l. 2. <hi>for</hi> from them, <hi>read</hi> for Women. <hi>In Margin</hi> Pſal. 92.13. l. 32. <hi>r.</hi> my. p. 21. l. 14. <hi>dele</hi> the. l. 20. <hi>r.</hi> were. p. 25. l. 43. <hi>r.</hi> they will. p. 27. l. 19. <hi>r.</hi> weep thus, <hi>dele</hi> this. l. 34. <hi>inſert</hi> and thine, <hi>dele</hi> and. p. 28. l. 28. <hi>r.</hi> thee. p. 32. <hi>in Margin inſert</hi> Dan. 4.31.32. Jer. 51.9. p. 38. l. 30. <hi>dele</hi> a. p. 40. l. 42. <hi>in Margin</hi> Deut. 32.4. l. 45. <hi>dele</hi> the. p. 43. l. 32. <hi>inſert</hi> for. p. 48. l. 12. <hi>in Margin</hi> 2 King. 6.16, 23. <hi>to</hi> l. 46. <hi>in Margin</hi> Dan. 4.12, 13. p. 50. l. 25. <hi>for</hi> ſecured, <hi>read</hi> ſoured. p. 53. l. 38. <hi>read</hi> we may be.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA in the Second Part.</head>
            <p>PAg. 10. <hi>in</hi> Gloria Patri, <hi>read</hi> To God, to Father, Son. p. 21. l. 22. <hi>inſert</hi> are given us. p. 24. l. 20. <hi>dele</hi> as thou didſt the Prophet, <hi>which is twice repeated.</hi> p. 26. l. 14. <hi>for</hi> O Lord, <hi>read</hi> O God. <hi>remove the * from</hi> l. 24. <hi>to</hi> l. 20. p. 35. l. 16. <hi>read</hi> eſtabliſh his Kingdom. p. 41. l. 32. <hi>read</hi> and a fruitful. p. 45. l. 16. <hi>in Margin</hi> Iſa. 36.10. p. 48. l. 2. <hi>in Margin</hi> Ruth 2.4. p. 49. l. 17. <hi>read</hi> the Rods. l. 33. <hi>read</hi> preſerved it. p. 50. l. 4. <hi>read</hi> thou. p. 55. l. 32. <hi>read</hi> Jewiſh. l. 33. <hi>in Margin</hi> Jer. 38.12, 13. p. 56. l. 2. <hi>in Margin</hi> Jonas 2.5, 6. l. 17. <hi>read</hi> this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate. p. 60. l. 6. <hi>for</hi> Loving, <hi>read</hi> Leaving the Breaſt. p. 61. l. 6. <hi>read</hi> Root. p. 62. l. 3. <hi>read</hi> Uzzah. l. 23. <hi>read</hi> Rereward. p. 64. <hi>in Margin, read</hi> Clarius. <hi>in</hi> l. 23. <hi>read</hi> ſedem innuit Aris. p. 68. <hi>in Marg. † read</hi> nictaturus ſim. p. 79. l. 13. <hi>read</hi> but to the people who watched there. p. 84. l. 17. <hi>read</hi> Songs of Elevation. <hi>And note: This whole 84th Page ſhould have been the firſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199576:9"/>
            <head>THE FIRST Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXX. <hi>PSALM.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>It is a Complaint, and Prayer againſt the falſneſs, fraud, and impious Deſigns, rather than the force, of inhumane Adverſaries: Becauſe their Strength and Power may (at leaſt for a Time) be from God's Will and Permiſſion; but Deceit and Perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs owe their Birth to Men's Prevarications, and the ſubtil Temptations of the Evil One: And therefore ought the rather to be deprecated.</p>
               <p>The Author of this Pſalm is not known, but ſuppoſed to be <hi>David,</hi> and made by him upon the like occaſion that the <hi>7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,</hi> the <hi>34<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,</hi> and the <hi>52<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                  </hi> were Compoſed, when he fled to <hi>Gath, ob Aethiopem Jeminienſem,</hi> (as<note n="*" place="margin">In Pſal. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Caſtalio</hi> phraſeth it) or upon the implacable Fury of <hi>Saul;</hi> truly and tivilly, as well as elegantly ſtiled, <hi>A melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly terrible Man:</hi> Or elſe upon the malicious Information of a <hi>Cuſhite</hi> or <hi>Edomite</hi> againſt an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> indeed, in whom there was no guile; which ſeems very probable from his Deſcription of the Parties, who were after the way of <hi>Meſech</hi> (as the <hi>Aethiopians Cuſhites</hi> were) and allied to the ſordid Tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> or <hi>Arabia;</hi> of which Country <hi>Doeg</hi> was a Native.</p>
               <p>This Pſalm likewiſe looks Prophetically at the ſworn Enemies of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>'s Peace; ſuch as were the confederate <hi>Arabians</hi> and <hi>Aſiaticks</hi> at the building the Temple, and afterwards with <hi>Antiochus,</hi> at the defacing of the ſame: All which cruel and cunning Foes are expreſſed by<note n="*" place="margin">Ezck, 38.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:199576:10"/>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N my di╌ſtreſs and fear,<note place="margin">For S. <hi>Steven</hi>'s day, or ſome time of Trial.</note> I cry'd unto the Lord; who ſoon did help, as hear, when I this wiſh did word; From Lips, made foul by guile and wrongs, and from falſe Tongues, Lord ſave my Soul.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quid tibi da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit? aut quid addet tibi?</hi> Spoken as to <hi>Saul</hi> (perhaps) by the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, upon the account of <hi>Doeg,</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>What Praiſe? what Profit ſhall</l>
                  <l>The treacherous Tongue bring thee?</l>
                  <l>Poor Soul! 'twill ſcorch and Gall</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelf, as well as me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Twill doubly harm,<note place="margin">Having been ſtreightned in my Verſe, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to obſerve in Proſe the rare Elegancy of the Pſalmiſt here; who ſpeaking of a deſert ſtate and place among the Sons of <hi>Iſmael,</hi> (the great Archer) he tells his ſavage Foes, (though Companions) that they ſhall be ſtruck with their own Weapons, as <hi>Saul</hi> was; and burnt with the Coals of the Wilderneſs, where Juniper moſt abounds, which was the moſt deſolate and grievous Fire, from the nature of the Wood; and ſo proper fuel for the black Tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> and for <hi>Meſech;</hi> (the <hi>Aſiaticks</hi>) if taken for a People wild, and wandering about in Wagons, or living in Tents covered with Skins: But if it referrs to a place, it is well rendered by the LXXII. whom I follow, with <hi>Symachus</hi> and <hi>Aquila,</hi> &amp;c,</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>By Fire; and Shot</l>
                  <l>Like Darts made hot</l>
                  <l>From ſome ſtrong Arm.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:199576:10"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why then? O why ſo long</l>
                  <l>Do I protract my Woes?</l>
                  <l>By wand'ring ſtill among</l>
                  <l>War's Friends, and Peace's Foes:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I'm in a Tent</l>
                  <l>Who are on Theft;</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Arabs</hi> left,</l>
                  <l>And Murder bent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>At me their Bows are bent,</l>
                  <l>Their Malice doth encreaſe;</l>
                  <l>They ſay no good I meant,</l>
                  <l>When I did ſeek their Peace:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When I ſpeak fair,</l>
                  <l>And ſtraight the Swarm</l>
                  <l>I them all-arm,</l>
                  <l>Their Stings prepare.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Corollarium <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Which may be uſed, or omitted,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>It being another Repetition of the Sence</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>It being another Return of the Muſick</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>It being another Recollection of the Pſalm.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <lg>
                  <l>BUT though the Sland'rers ſting,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ver.</hi> 3, 4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Like Lightning, pierc'd and burn'd:</l>
                  <l>The Stones which he did ſling,</l>
                  <l>Heav'n in his Face return'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Live Coals from Hell,</l>
                  <l>By his bad Tongue,</l>
                  <l>And Javelings flung</l>
                  <l>On his Head fell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therefore no more will I</l>
                  <l>Be of ſuch Bruits afraid;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ver. 2, 7.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>No more I'll ſigh, or cry,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ver.</hi> 5, 6.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though I'm in Deſerts ſtay'd:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In all my Ways</l>
                  <l>Who doſt afford</l>
                  <l>I'll Bleſs Thee, Lord,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ver.</hi> 1, 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such cauſe of Praiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199576:11"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though I'm in Deſerts ſtay'd,</l>
                  <l>No more I'll ſigh, or cry:</l>
                  <l>Or be of Bruits afraid,</l>
                  <l>No longer now will I.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such cauſe of Praiſe</l>
                  <l>We'll Bleſs Thee, Lord,</l>
                  <l>Thou doſt afford;</l>
                  <l>In all our Ways.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri, &amp;c.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Glory be to our King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who ſhall be, was, and is;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Loud</hi> Hallelujahs <hi>ſing</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To God, the God of Peace:</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Lord of Hoſts,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Father, Son,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Three in One,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:199576:11"/>
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Firſt <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXX. PSALM.</head>
               <p>O Lord, our Redeemer! a very preſent help in trouble, as I have found thee heretofore, bleſſed be thy powerful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, ſo I deſire to approve thee whenſoever, as at this time, I cry unto thee to deliver my Soul. O God! I ſee that I am fallen into a dangerous Condition, by the Lies of the Serpent, the Treacheries of my own Fleſh, and the Falſhoods of the World, which I have ſought and ſerved, liſtened and truſted to, and ſo am juſtly appay'd with Couſenage and Diſgrace, with Calumnies and Accuſation. For what can be had from the Accuſer of the Brethren, from the deceitfulneſs of Riches, and from the Cheats of all things here below, but diſappointments, and vexation for ſuch as follow lying Vanities, forſaking thy Mercies, and their own?</p>
               <p>Alas! then woe is me! that I have heaped up ſuch Coals of Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on my own Head, and pierced my Heart through with ſo many Darts of Sorrow, by not delighting in the Tents of the Righteous, nor in the Tabernacles of thy Holineſs, but in the Dwellings of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs, and in the Houſe of the Accurſed; ſo that I have deſerved indeed to be made a Vagabond like <hi>Cain,</hi> and a Slave like <hi>Cham,</hi> in a perpetual Baniſhment from Comfort, and in a Captivity unto Sin, by having my Converſation according to the evil faſhion of this Age.</p>
               <p>But, Lord! how long, how long ſhall I ſojourn, either amongſt the Enemies of thy Grace, or of my Peace? Amongſt the Superſtitious or Idolatrous? Amongſt thoſe who are after the way of <hi>Meſech?</hi> Or thoſe who dwell in the black aboads of <hi>Kedar?</hi> O! prolong not my Danger and Unhappineſs any more among them, nor protract my Wandrings with a backſliding People; for I ſeek Peace, Peace with Thee, with my own Conſcience, and with all the World.</p>
               <p>But <hi>can the</hi> Egyptian <hi>change his Skin? Had</hi> Zimri <hi>Peace, who ſlew his Maſter?</hi> No Lord. <hi>There is no Peace</hi> (thou haſt ſaid it) <hi>to the Wicked,</hi> who are at defiance with thee, and with themſelves, and make War in the face of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Therefore that I may find Peace, I ſeek thy Pardon, and my Soul's Purity, and deſire thee to preſerve me from the Pollutions and Snares of a perverſe Generation, that diſſemble as ſtrange Children, that ſo (having no fellowſhip with the workers of Iniquity) I might live in the ſweet Communion of thy Saints, and to be furthered by their Examples and Converſation in the way of Peace and Holineſs.</p>
               <p>For, Lord! I would be a pacifick <hi>Jacob,</hi> and dwell under the ſhadow of thy Wings, there accounting my ſelf ſecure though I have no other
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199576:12"/>Covering. Thou art the beſt place to hide me in, and 'tis not my Sword or Bow ſhall ſettle or ſecure me, but thy Mercy, thy Grace, and thy Spirit. No ſtrange Arms here can give me a certain or ſafe Abode, unleſs thou be on my ſide.</p>
               <p>Therefore, dear God! whilſt many riſe up againſt me to trouble me, in ſaying, <hi>Where is thy God?</hi> (ſeeking to deſtroy me with their own quiet) be thou a God nigh at hand to deliver me from Treachery, Malice, Turbulence, and Hypocriſie. And while my Foes heap Coals of Fire on their own Heads by unjuſt Actions, and hard Speeches, let my Mouth be touched with a Coal from thine Altar, that I may know how to keep the Door of my Lips from all Curſing and Bitterneſs, Lying and Blaſphemies, fraudulent and filthy Communication; and how to open it in Praying to thee, that I may find the Bleſſings of Peace within, above, abroad, about me, by Repentance of my Sins, Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my Life, Regeneration of my Nature, and Reconciliation to thy Love.</p>
               <p>O! let it ſuffice that I have ſtayed ſo long in their Habitations, where the Inſtruments of Cruelty remain, where I might have been drawn either unto baſe Earthly Sorrow and Diſtraction, or to foul Helliſh Guilt and Deſperation, and ſo to inevitable Deſtruction both of Soul and Body. Let it pity thee to ſee my poor Soul in ſuch a Sink, ſuch a Gaol and Mill, in ſuch a naſty, vile, and ſlaviſh State as it hath endured. And do thou cover my Head while my Foes make them ready to Battel.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall I be guarded from the ſtrife of Tongues, from the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of Sinners, from the reproach that I fear, and from <hi>Satan</hi> that is come forth againſt me with great wrath, becauſe I have called on thy Name, while thou art not angry that I cry unto thee,</p>
               <p>Our Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:199576:12"/>
            <head>THE SECOND Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXXI. <hi>PSALM,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Is an Act of Acquieſcence and Truſt in God's Power and Preſence, made by <hi>David</hi> (as it is thought) when hunted like a Partridg on the Mountains; and purſued by <hi>Saul,</hi> when he made the <hi>54<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 55<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,</hi> and <hi>57<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> Pſalm: And this, being much uſed by the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Babylon,</hi> (as moſt ſuitable for times of Perſecution or Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) was at their going up from thence appointed to be one of their Pſalms of Aſcents, and therefore to be ſung frequently, loudly, and by Reſponſes; which occaſioned this Compoſing it like an Anthem, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: The Stanza's being ſo pointed and divided as to anſwer alternately by Diſticks (if it may better ſuit the Muſick.)</p>
               <p>The Title of it hath a difference from the reſt, (as the <hi>Rabbins</hi> obſerve) being <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and not as in others <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</p>
               <p>It may be ſtiled <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>March,</hi> made by him (or ſome other conſiderable Perſon) while be kept the Field, either for the ſafety of his Flocks (as <hi>Jacob</hi> did), or of his Friends (as <hi>Abram</hi>): Thus did the Royal Shepherd, and ſweet Singer of <hi>Iſrael</hi> exerciſe, and employ his Mind in the grateful Memory of the Divine Goodneſs. Well might he then here pray and hope like a Souldier, that God would be his Shade (as well as his Shield) as near to him as his ſhadow; that the Sun might not hurt him by Day, nor the Moon by Night, (as <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and <hi>Achitophel,</hi> the one by Day, and the other by Night, intended to have done.)</p>
               <p>And if we look on <hi>David,</hi> as he went up the Aſcent of Mount <hi>Olivet:</hi> This Pſalm was very proper for his Condition then, as it is for any Perſon's now, in the interval of War; the Phraſes being throughout the whole Pſalm Military; and alluſive to Souldiers beſieged, as in the firſt Verſe; relieved, as in the ſecond; all-arm'd, as in the third; ſecured, watched, and guarded, as in the fourth; ſhielded and ſurrounded, as in the fifth and ſixth; in the ſeventh and eighth hemm'd in, and convoy'd out for Victory and Triumph.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:199576:13"/>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here ſhall I ſeek for aid?<note place="margin">For the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> and <hi>October.</hi>
                  </note> where ſhall I ſet mine Eyes? mine Eyes and Pray'rs, like Birds afraid, up to the Hills would riſe. But whither would they riſe? un╌to ſome dangerous height? O no, this Quarry thither flies, whence ſprings our help, and light.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:199576:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor hath our Health and Light</l>
                  <l>From things below their Birth:</l>
                  <l>But from the higheſt Rock of Might,</l>
                  <l>Who made both Heav'n and Earth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therefore, though falſe foul Earth</l>
                  <l>Thy Soul with Foes ſurround:</l>
                  <l>Shall it be mov'd from holy Mirth?</l>
                  <l>Shall Cares run it on Ground?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Chriſt is the Ark to ground<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.11.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy Heart on, when diſtreſt:</l>
                  <l>From head to foot he'll make thee ſound;</l>
                  <l>On him did <hi>Jacob</hi> reſt.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.11.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But he doth never reſt<note place="margin">Non dormita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, multo minùs dormiet, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: quamvis <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; ex impatientiâ Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentis Deus ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dormire dicitur. <hi>Pſal. 44.24.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>From doing good, nor ſleeps:</l>
                  <l>That with ſuch Guards thou may'ſt be bleſt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>As he his <hi>Iſrael</hi> keeps.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Good Shepherd he doth keep<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.1, 4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>His Flock, ev'n in Death's ſhade:</l>
                  <l>See then (if thou art of his Sheep)</l>
                  <l>How on thy ſide he's laid.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though Dangers have way-laid</l>
                  <l>Thy going out, or in:</l>
                  <l>See how thy Husband's Arm's diſplay'd,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſave thy very Skin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like the three Children's Skin,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.27.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thine ſhall be ſcorch'd by none:</l>
                  <l>Whatever Heat thou may'ſt be in,</l>
                  <l>Whatever Star hath ſhown.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor ſhall the Moon, nor Sun</l>
                  <l>Hurt thee, by Night or Day:</l>
                  <l>No Miſchief ſeen, nor cloſely done,</l>
                  <l>Shall touch thee any way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>God ſhall preſerve thy Ways</l>
                  <l>And Mind, from all that's ill</l>
                  <l>In Youth: And when thy Life decays,</l>
                  <l>Bleſſed thou ſhalt be ſtill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then truſt and bleſs him ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Who endleſs Safety ſends:</l>
                  <l>God through this Vale of Sorrows, will</l>
                  <l>Guide us to joyful ends.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:199576:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Entrance, Progreſs, Ends,</l>
                  <l>Public and private Pow'rs;</l>
                  <l>Labours, and Studies of his Friends,</l>
                  <l>God bleſſes at all hours.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then truſt and bleſs him ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Who ſtill did us defend:</l>
                  <l>God doth, and ever will,</l>
                  <l>Give Bleſſings without end:<note place="margin">Antiſtrophe.</note> Give Bleſſings without end,</l>
                  <l>God doth and ever will;</l>
                  <l>He ſtill did us defend,</l>
                  <l>Then truſt and bleſs him ſtill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Entrance, Progreſs, Ends,</l>
                  <l>Public and private Pow'rs:</l>
                  <l>And Works of all his Friends,</l>
                  <l>God bleſſes: Lord bleſs Ours.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri, &amp;c.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Father, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Son,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And to the Holy-Ghoſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Be Glory: And let ev'ry one</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Strive who ſhall praiſe God moſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:199576:14"/>
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Second <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXI. PSALM.</head>
               <p>I Will lift up my Heart to thee, O Lord! And though it be caſt down with the dangers and diffidence I am in, while mine Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and mine Enemies have caſt a Mount about me, to hinder me from the ſight and hope of Succour, yet have I God's Hill to fly unto; and from thy Houſe I can ſurvey the end of the Wicked, the Redemption of thy Captives, and the height of thy Power, that is higher than the higheſt. But O the depth of thy Love! What a pleaſant Vale is this under it? How doth this ſmile and ſing, and ſtand full of Corn, that ſtrengthens Man's Heart? So that <hi>although I remain in the Valley of the ſhadow of Death,</hi> if I can but look up to the Rock that is higher than I, to Chriſt (the <hi>Shecinah</hi>) the true <hi>Mercy Seat,</hi> that is placed above the <hi>Cherubims,</hi> all Types and Symbols of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, I ſhall neither loſe my Faith, nor my Life; I ſhall not be diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitted, nor enſlaved like a ſurprized <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> I ſhall not be famiſhed, nor broken up like a long beſieged <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Though mine Enemies hem me in on every ſide, and carnal Fear cauſe me to cry out (as the Prophet's Servant) <hi>What ſhall we do?</hi> Yet if I can but lift up mine Eyes to thee, which indeed are naturally as heavy as <hi>Moſes</hi> his Hand, I ſhall perceive ſomewhat elſe beſides Perils and Foes on every ſide, I ſhall find the Mountains full of Chariots of Fire, and more for me than can be againſt me. For an Hoſt of Angels ſhall pitch their Tents about me to ſecure me, and thoſe mighty Miniſters of thy good pleaſure ſhall keep me like <hi>Daniel</hi> from the power of the Lyon. So that my moſt Savage Enemies ſhall lack and ſuffer hunger, while I want nothing that is good. For though my way be hedged up that I cannot paſs which way I would, nor follow the Luſts of my Heart, and the deſires of mine Eyes, as many do, yet I may look up with joy and confidence (as I truſt I ſhall) at the laſt day, becauſe my Salvation is drawing nigh.</p>
               <p>My Hope, my Help, cometh from the Lord, not from the Angels in his Preſence, but from the Angel of his Preſence, and of his Covenant, the Bleſſed <hi>JESUS,</hi> who having taken our Nature that he might be ſenſible of our Infirmities, ever abides with Humanity, at thy right Hand making Interceſſion for us. And as he made the Heavens and the Earth for us, ſo he makes a new Heaven and a new Earth of us, by juſtifying and ſanctifying both our Souls and Bodies, through the mighty Work of his Spirit, in his Word and Sacraments: For theſe are the Mountains of the Lord, wherein he is apparently ſeen, Glorious in Holineſs, Fearful in Praiſes, doing Wonders, and abounding in Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Truth. If we Worſhip him (as our Fathers did) in theſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199576:15"/>Mountains, in the heights of Sincerity and Devotion, we may expect to hear God promiſing us graciouſly, as he did <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he will be a God to us, and to our Seed after us: And we may hope to ſee him, as <hi>Manoah</hi> and his Wife did, in the Zealous performances of his holy Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in the Flame ariſing from the Altar of our Hearts; from whence God would not accept a Service, if he deſired the Death of Sinners.</p>
               <p>Therefore we may be aſſured, that if we keep in his ways he will keep us in ours, as he did his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> both by the Pillar of Fire, and by the Pillar of a Cloud; by the flame of Affliction, as well as by the light of Proſperity. And while we lay hold on theſe, (as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did on the two Columns) let us invoke thy help, O Lord; ſaying,</p>
               <p>O Lord! Though thou mayeſt call to Baldneſs, to Weeping, to Weakneſs, or to Want; though thou mayeſt touch the Sinew, and make it ſhrink; or ſtrive with me as thou didſt with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and begin to afflict me, or ſeem to depart from me, ſo that my Fleſh and my Heart may fail, yet O ſuffer not my Soul to ſlip, let not my Foot my Foundation be removed, but let it reſt with thy <hi>Dove</hi> upon the <hi>Ark of thy Covenant,</hi> and be fixed on the Rock <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> that thou mayeſt order all my goings.</p>
               <p>O! do thou go out and in before me, that my going out and coming in may be ever bleſſed. If thou go not out with us, carry us not abroad, nor let us ſtay at home without thee. Let not the Vanities of the Day, nor the Viſions of the Night, diſturb our Senſes, or abuſe our Souls. O Lord, prevent the Mid-day Devils, and the Arrows that fly by Noon, from blaſting or hurting of us; nor let Nocturnal Evils, or any miſchief in the dark, have Power to ſmite us: But be thou a Succour, a Second, a God, not a far off, to preſerve and proſper us in all our Actions, publick and private, in our Labours, in our Studies, in our Reſt, in our Retirements, in our weak Beginnings, in our happier Progreſſes, and in our beſt Concluſions. O Lord, be with us in our entrance on the Stage of this World, in our Parts here, in our Exit hence, even now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:199576:15"/>
            <head>THE THIRD Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXXII. <hi>PSALM,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Deſeribeth <hi>David</hi>'s Joy, which is expreſſed in the <hi>30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> Pſalm, at the bringing of the Ark, and Offering for the Temple, and Dedication of his Houſe to God's Service: And it is a Preparative Hymn for the Devout, in their going up to the Places of Religion and Solemn Worſhip; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining their Thanks, Praiſe, and Pleaſure, in the return of the Comfort and Company, which they enjoyed in the public Adoration of God; and their Prayers for the longer continuance of ſuch ſignal Bleſſings: Made by <hi>David</hi> (as it is thought) upon his return to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> after his flight from <hi>Abſalom;</hi> and ſolemnly ſung by the <hi>Levites</hi> at their coming out of Captivity. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in general (as the Temple more eſpecially) being the Type of God's Church, both Militant and Triumphant, that is built with the precious Stones of the Apoſtles and Prophets, <hi>CHRIST</hi> himſelf being the Rock, <hi>Caput Anguli, &amp; Caput Angelorum;</hi> to whom when many come, there is much Joy.</p>
               <p>The Poem is Dramatick, (like the <hi>118<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> Pſalm) in which the King, Prieſt, and People, ſeem to bear their Parts of Rejoycing at the public Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals (which were thrice every Year to be ſolemnized at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Command of God; which occaſioned the great Beautifying, Enlarging, and Fortifying of that City, intimated in the <hi>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,</hi> and <hi>7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> Verſes; as well as the other reaſon of its Happineſs and Amplitude, (from the Temple of God, and Throne of <hi>David</hi>) mentioned in the <hi>1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>, 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,</hi> and <hi>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> Verſes: To which may be added this reaſon, becauſe there was the great Senate of the LXXII. or <hi>Sanhedrim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King beginneth the Pſalm in the <hi>1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>
                  </hi> Verſe, the Prieſts follow in the <hi>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>,</hi> the People in the <hi>3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>,</hi> and they go on in the <hi>4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</hi> Then the King takes it again in the <hi>5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,</hi> the Prieſts in the <hi>6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,</hi> and the People go on in the <hi>7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> (as in a Proceſſion, and good order): The Prieſts take it again in the <hi>8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,</hi> and the the King concludes in the beſt, (though laſt place) with a fixt and pious Reſolution.</p>
               <p>This may properly be ſet for the <hi>29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> of <hi>May.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:199576:16"/>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſ╌ſed be God for the good News, and Freedom, which he doth afford: From th'Houſe of Bondage, like glad <hi>Jews,</hi> we come un╌to thy Houſe, O Lord.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our Woes and Wand'rings now ſhall ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>While rooted faſt, like Trees, we ſtand</l>
                  <l>Within thy Courts; who doſt with Peace</l>
                  <l>Plant us again in our Land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our Joys ſhoot up with freſh encreaſe,</l>
                  <l>While rooted faſt, like Trees, we ſtand</l>
                  <l>Within thy Courts; who doſt with Peace</l>
                  <l>Plant us again in our own Land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>See,<note place="margin">Hieroſolyma optimè inſtituta concors, &amp; ideo duratura.</note> ſee, how comely! how compact!</l>
                  <l>Peace makes this Gyant-City ſeem:</l>
                  <l>Our Union makes her Form exact,</l>
                  <l>Like th' Heav'nly New <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whither, to an Eternal Feaſt</l>
                  <l>All the Lord's Tribes at laſt ſhall go;</l>
                  <l>And on his Hill above find reſt,</l>
                  <l>As we do in his Houſe below.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here now, (as at a Paſſover)</l>
                  <l>Our Tribes (like Streams) i' th' Ocean meet;</l>
                  <l>To ſerve thee, as thy Laws averr:</l>
                  <l>And Praiſe thy Name, that is ſo great.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:199576:16"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here now, (as at a Paſſover)</l>
                  <l>Our Tribes (like Streams) i' th' Ocean meet;</l>
                  <l>To ſerve thee, as thy Statutes are:</l>
                  <l>And Praiſe thy Name, that is ſo great.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here is God's Temple, <hi>David</hi>'s Throne,</l>
                  <l>The Bench of Juſtice, Mercy's Seat:</l>
                  <l>Here Princes, Prophets, Prieſts make known</l>
                  <l>How good our Church! our State how great!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here's the Bleſt Type of Heav'n above,</l>
                  <l>Pray then for <hi>Salem;</hi> here for Peace:</l>
                  <l>Since they who love this Place, do prove</l>
                  <l>Happy, and bleſt with much Encreaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lord, bleſs us, and this Place, with Peace,</l>
                  <l>With Plenty, and with Piety:</l>
                  <l>For thy Name's ſake, let our's encreaſe,</l>
                  <l>Our King's, and Friends Proſperity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All Tyes, both Humane, and Divine;</l>
                  <l>Our Love for Men, our Zeal for God,</l>
                  <l>What we can do, or wiſh, combine<note place="margin">Fiat Pax in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temurali tuo, &amp; Abundantia, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. in Palatiis, Turrium ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar ſtructis.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſeek the Bliſs of this aboad.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In the Lord's Praiſe let none be Dumb,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But Father, Son, and Ghoſt adore;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who was, and is, and is to come,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thrice Bleſſed God for evermore.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Third <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXII. PSALM.</head>
               <p>O Glorious God! to whom Praiſe and Worſhip is due, to whom Vengeance and Holineſs belongs; accept the Joys, and Adorations of our Souls and Bodies, for that we have not only Freedom in our own Perſons, but alſo Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from our Relations to come along with them, and many more of thy People, to the moſt proper place, and by the appointed way, of public Worſhipping and Praiſing of thee.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199576:17"/>
               <p>Oh! how glad (as if we had found great Spoils) may we be to find, not only that we can, but alſo that others will plant themſelves within thy Courts, and not ſtand in the way of Sinners, that we may proſper together like Trees by the Water ſide, and bring forth Fruit, and that in due ſeaſon?</p>
               <p>Dear, and gracious Lord! when we go hence, and ſhall be called away by Death, how happy ſhould we be, could we come to thee as eaſily as we now can come to the Church, and bring this <hi>Olive-branch</hi> in our Mouths into thy Ark!</p>
               <p>Let us go up into the Houſe of the Lord, let us aſcend unto his holy Hill; let us be tranſplanted from the Gates of Death, to be rooted in the Porches of the <hi>New Jeruſalem;</hi> for one day in thy Courts is better than a thouſand in any other. <hi>I had rather be a Door-keeper in thy Tabernacle, than to dwell in the Tents of Wickedneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Help us then to joyn with the bleſſed Choir, both of the Church Militant and Triumphant, in a Leſſon of the beſt Service, even Love and Charity, which is the compleateſt Religion, the fulfiller of the Law, the filler full of Heaven.</p>
               <p>For ſee the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that comes down thence, as well as that which is above, agrees in all its Parts and Graces, and by its lovely Symmetry makes up the ſweeteſt Harmony of Heaven and Earth, declaring Charity the bond of Peace, as Peace the breeder of Felicity.</p>
               <p>Therefore while we ſee the preſent Concord and Conformity thou haſt afforded our Nation, we look with joy upon an Emblem of that glorious Day, when thou ſhalt gather thy Children from the four Winds, and bring them together in the Clouds, to meet the Lord in the Air, and to live with him for ever.</p>
               <p>Lord! 'till that time come, preſerve thy Church among us from Rent and Spot, from Breach and Blemiſh, and meet with us graciouſly (as thou didſt with <hi>Elijah</hi>) in the ſoft mild Voice of thy Goſpel, in the favoury Breath of thy Spirit, in the ſweet Airs of our pious and public Services; wherein make us to conſent to Pray for the Peace of our Souls, and of thy People; as alſo for the Plenty of our Land, for the Piety of our Governours, for the Proſperity of their Government and Perſons; for the Purity of Religion, for the Perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity of thy Church among us; as alſo for Unanimity, and Uniformity in the way of thy Worſhip, that we may endeavour, as well as deſire, the moſt durable Good here, and an eternal Good hereafter, to our ſelves, and ours, and all thine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which we beſeech thee grant for</hi> Jeſus Chriſt<hi>'s ſake, who is of the Stock and Lineage of</hi> David, <hi>to whom belongs the Seat of Judgment for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:199576:17"/>
            <head>THE FOURTH Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXXIII. <hi>PSALM,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Is agreeable to the condition of <hi>David</hi> in the third Pſalm; as alſo to the ſad State of the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> Compoſed (perhaps) by <hi>Ezra</hi> at <hi>Babylon,</hi> and from that time frequent in uſe; being Calculated for the Times of Trouble and Tyranny. Wherein the Church (as under <hi>Antiochus,</hi> or ſome ſuch inſulting Oppreſſor) prayeth, complaineth, and truſts to God.</p>
               <p>The Prieſt beginning (as it were with an <hi>Oremus</hi>) to the People in the firſt Verſe; and then the whole Congregation joyning and going on with him to the end of the Pſalm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O thee, who doſt a╌bide, a╌bove the Starry Spheres, yet haſt our Griefs with Pi╌ty ey'd; to thee we ſend our Tears.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:199576:18"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>To Heav'n this Spring of Tears</l>
                  <l>From hence doth bubling riſe;</l>
                  <l>Which from low Grounds our Paſſion rears<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121.1</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To thee, that haſt our Eyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor do we need an Eye,<note place="margin">By <hi>Hand</hi> in the Text is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood <hi>help, ſtrength,</hi> or <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection;</hi> by thoſe who take the words of this Verſe to imply the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant's repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Lord for <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence</hi> from Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign <hi>injuries.</hi> It alſo ſignifies <hi>bounty, directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> to thoſe who take the meaning as I apprehend it.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But to obſerve thy Hands:</l>
                  <l>Which way for Bleſſing us they lye;</l>
                  <l>By Chaſt'nings, or Commands.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since oft, like <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Hands,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.14, 19.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thine, as a-croſs, are ſpread;</l>
                  <l>For God (not Man) beſt underſtands</l>
                  <l>How to Crown <hi>Ephraim</hi>'s Head.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therefore we raiſe our Heads,</l>
                  <l>Not to repine, but pray;</l>
                  <l>To mark how our chief <hi>Joſhua</hi> leads,</l>
                  <l>And how we him obey.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As Soldiers ſtill obey</l>
                  <l>Their Leader's Staff, and Rod,</l>
                  <l>And at their Becks do go or ſtay;</l>
                  <l>So wait we on our God.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy Smile or Frowns, O God,</l>
                  <l>Like humbleſt Handmaids, we</l>
                  <l>Do bear; and from our Lord's aboad</l>
                  <l>Do not (like <hi>Hagar</hi>) flee.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.14.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No <hi>Jonas</hi> here will fly<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jon.</hi> 1.3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>From thee;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jon.</hi> 4.8.</note> (though Chaſten'd) thus</l>
                  <l>We,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 5.2.</note> as meek Servants, carefully</l>
                  <l>Stay, 'till thou pity us.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy Mercy we implore,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſpeedy Mercy,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Multum ſatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata eſt Anima ſubſannatione:</hi> As if play'd upon, and ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed at, by the Soldiery, while led in Triumph; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the expreſſion in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.3.</note> Lord:</l>
                  <l>For now our Lives are ſcorn'd; nay more,</l>
                  <l>Our very Souls abhorr'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By thoſe we are abhorr'd,</l>
                  <l>(As we do loath their Pride)</l>
                  <l>Who can with Inſolence afford</l>
                  <l>To wrong us, and deride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But God ſhall them deride,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Scorns o're-charge our Hearts;</l>
                  <l>When theſe are full, and can abide</l>
                  <l>No more, God takes our parts.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:199576:18"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſince God takes our parts,</l>
                  <l>To him our Tears ſhall glide:</l>
                  <l>To him we'll lift our Looks and Hearts,</l>
                  <l>Who doth in Heav'n abide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now ſince God takes our part,</l>
                  <l>To him our Tears ſhall glide:</l>
                  <l>To him we'll lift our Looks and Hearts,</l>
                  <l>Who doth in Heav'n abide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All Glory, Praiſe, and Bliſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To th' Three, in Unity;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who (as at firſt) was God, now is,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And evermore ſhall be.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Fourth <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXIII. PSALM.</head>
               <p>O Thou great Lord and King, that dwelleſt in the Heavens! <hi>David</hi> hath taught me to lift up mine Eyes to thee, and the Son of <hi>David</hi> hath better inſtructed me to call thee by thy Spirit, <hi>Abba, Father which art in Heaven, Hallowed be thy Name,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That gracious Name of <hi>Our Father,</hi> invites us, Lord, to call upon thee <hi>in the needful time of Trouble.</hi> For though thou dwelleſt in the higheſt Heavens, thou art not contained by them; but from that thy Throne, vouchſafeſt to look down upon what is done and ſuffered upon Earth. So that in the deepeſt evils of our Sufferance, as in all the good of our Enjoyment here, we may ſtill look up, and ſee thy doing, and be ſatisfied in the Wonder that thou doſt ſo much for our advantage.</p>
               <p>Ah! how marvellous is it in our Eyes, that when Hope and Help both fail on Earth, we can ſeek much higher for them, and even then too, when we are juſtly corrected; becauſe thou art a merciful King, and behold we are thy Servants for all that thou haſt afforded us.</p>
               <p>We ſubmit to thee with humble Fear, and wait on thee with Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, and Praiſe thee for ſmiting and ſubduing us thy People under
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199576:19"/>thee. For thou doſt as the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did to <hi>Benhadad;</hi> thou beateſt, that thou mayeſt bring us to thy ſelf; thou conquereſt, that thou mayeſt be kind; taking away a little, that thou mighteſt give a better Kingdom. Wherefore we beg, and truſt, that when thou haſt convinced us how worthy we all are of Hate, Death, and Diſgrace, that then thou wilt reſtore us to Life, Favour, and Proſperity.</p>
               <p>Well may we be watchful Suppliants and Expectants for ſome Token of thy Pity, when thy left Hand, ſome ſiniſter Providence is laid upon us, becauſe thou haſt ſtill thy right Hand, the Man of thy right Hand to embrace thy Spouſe, when thy afflicting Hand is never ſo heavy upon her, either by the Tyranny of Oppreſſors, or by the Rod of Tribulation.</p>
               <p>Let us rightly hearken to this Rod, and ſee the Hand which hath appointed it, and not look awry by Pride, Uncharitableneſs, Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, or Impatience, on what thou doſt; becauſe as thy provoked Juſtice is the Author, ſo our Provocations are the juſt Original of our Sorrows, and the Springs of our Sufferings. And it is well for us in our Calamities when we are not thrown out, but fall into the Hands of God, who is no leſs pitiful, than powerful, to deliver us with <hi>David</hi> out of the Hands of all our Enemies, and out of the Hands of <hi>Saul</hi> too: From all our wicked Foes, (I mean) and from our moſt wicked ſelves alſo; from our own Unrighteouſneſs, as well as others, which fills our Souls with Shame, our State with Contempt, and our Lives with Sorrow.</p>
               <p>For is not proud <hi>Lucifer,</hi> as it were, at eaſe, when we tumble our ſelves down by diffidence in God, or ſelf-deceit? And vile Oppreſſors, like the Devils themſelves, are in their proper and pleaſant work, when they are <hi>Lording it over thine Heritage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore preſerve us, we beſeech thee, from our own Baſeneſs and Falſhood, as well as from the Tyranny and Treachery of thine other Enemies. And plead thou our Cauſe for us with others, and with our ſelves, for thy Son's, and for our Soul's ſake.</p>
               <p>And when we are driven by the Inſolence of others, or by the Demerits of our own Actings, to implore thy Mercy, and thy Pity, with all the proſtitute Submiſſion, humble Confidence, and abſolute Reſignation of Obedient Servants. O! let us not be ſlothful in our Duties, or doubtful of thy Providence, but diligent in all the Labour that thou calleſt us to, thanking our ſelves for deſerving Correction, as thee our Lord for correcting us ſo Father-like, and truſting by thy Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements to prove in us more of thy Love, and of our Adoption.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:199576:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE FIFTH Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXXIV. <hi>PSALM,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Is entituled <hi>David</hi>'s, according to the Tenor of that in <hi>Samuel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 2. v. 22.</note> being a Commemoration of his wonderful deliverance from great and many Dangers; together with a thankful acknowledgment to God, the ſole Author of Safety and Succeſs, properly uſed at any time of eminent Preſervation; (as on the Fifth of <hi>November,</hi> or Third of <hi>June.</hi>)</p>
               <p>It may be called, <hi>David</hi>'s Triumphs for more than one Victory, by God's ſpecial aſſiſtance, as may be gathered from the repetition of the firſt words, <hi>(niſi quod Dominus)</hi> which imply the iteration of God's Goodneſs, and Man's gratitude; for when he is pleaſed to manifeſt the largeneſs of Loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs to us, then eſpecially ought we to make our return of Gratitude with a <hi>Non nobis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Divine <hi>Io Paean</hi> was compoſed (probably) after the Conqueſt of the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> who had beſet <hi>David</hi> on every ſide, according to that expreſſion of their force and inhumane Rage, <hi>Tunc homines (Adham per contemptum) vivos deglutiiſſent nos;</hi> or (as the word <hi>Adham</hi> ſeems to hint to me) upon his ſubduing of the <hi>Edomites,</hi> when he made the <hi>60<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> Pſalm; or (as others think) after moſt of his Victories over the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> &amp;c. in <hi>Chron.</hi> when the Snare was broke by the Death of his Enemies, as (in the Prophecy) the <hi>Jews</hi> Bondage was, by the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> breaking the <hi>Chaldean</hi> Monarchy.</p>
               <p>And ſo the late and former, the many and wonderful Deliverances of our Nation, are to own the immediate effect of God's gracious interpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and as a ſignall Evidence of His all-ſwaying Power, (as the firſt Creation of the World was) that we might not Sacrifice to our Nets and Bulwarks, nor value our ſelves upon the ſtore of deeper Waters (like once Proud, but now Deſolate, <hi>Tyre;</hi>) but that our Truſt, Succour, and Defence, may be founded on him, the Supreme of all Beings, on whom depends the whole Creation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="musical_Psalm">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:199576:20"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ad not the Lord been on our ſide, now may the wraſtling <hi>Iſ╌rael</hi> ſay, when <hi>E╌ſau</hi> did his Troops pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide; our Flocks had been the Ly╌ons prey.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Had not the Lord been on our ſide,</l>
                  <l>When Men againſt us roſe (like Waves);</l>
                  <l>The Surges of their Rage, and Pride,</l>
                  <l>Had ſnatcht us quick into our Graves.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like Whales upon <hi>Amittay</hi>'s Son,<note place="margin">Jonas.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Death's Jaws on us they open'd wide:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dathan</hi>'s ſtrange End,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.29.</note> how could we ſhun?</l>
                  <l>Had not the Lord been on our ſide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When Seas of Rage ſwell'd to that height,</l>
                  <l>As on our Souls to whelm their Tyde;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Torrents had deſtroy'd us quite,</l>
                  <l>Had not the Lord been on our ſide!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then had the Streams our ſtrength o're-pow'r'd,</l>
                  <l>But we through Floods, through Foes did wade:</l>
                  <l>And were not, as a Prey, devour'd;</l>
                  <l>Nor of their curſed Teeth afraid.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:199576:20"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bleſſed be God! our Life's got free</l>
                  <l>From all the Toyls, their Miſchief ſet:</l>
                  <l>As Birds out of a Snare, ſo we</l>
                  <l>'Scape ſtrangely through the Fowler's Net.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hell Snares are broke, our Souls are freed,</l>
                  <l>For on God's help our Hearts are ſtay'd:</l>
                  <l>God's Word ſpeaks Heav'n, and Earth his Deed;</l>
                  <l>His Hands preſerve the Works they made.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>God keep us all, as all he made;</l>
                  <l>From him the Heavens and Earth proceed:</l>
                  <l>Upon his Truth our Truſt is ſtay'd;</l>
                  <l>Hell's Snares are broke, and we are freed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Glory be to the Father, Son,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Holy-Ghoſt, whom we adore</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In Perſons three, in Eſſence one,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who was, is, ſhall be evermore.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Fifth <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXIV. PSALM.</head>
               <p>O Thou Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> thou Shepherd of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that leadeſt thy People like a Flock, while we with thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs look up to thy ſtrength for us, to thy ſtay of us, and thy ſtaff over us, let us look down with Humility on our own unworthineſs. We deſerve not the leaſt part of that care and watchfulneſs of thine, which defends us daily from the ravenous <hi>Bear</hi> of this World's Temptations, from the <hi>Uncircumciſed Philiſtine</hi> our own Fleſh, and from the roaring <hi>Lyon</hi> of the Abyſs, that goes about ſeeking to devour, to ſwallow us up quick, as it were, at a Morſel: And yet, bleſſed be the Lord, he hath not given us up for a Prey to theſe Deſtroyers; and if we give not up our ſelves by our ſinful fears, and eaſie ſubmiſſions, though <hi>Satan</hi>'s rage be like his Hell enflamed, he cannot have his will of us. That <hi>Lyon</hi> may come out againſt us with great wrath, and fright us by his vain Noiſes, but cannot fall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199576:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon us at once, as he deſires. He hath no part, no power of us, 'till we give it to him.</p>
               <p>If therefore, O Lord, we are on thy ſide, or thou on ours, we need not fear what Devils, or what Man can do unto us, even when they riſe never ſo proudly, never ſo powerfully againſt us. Let us but ſet the Lord our Righteouſneſs at our right hands; let us but have righteous Hands, and innocent Hearts, and we ſhall not be ſo greatly moved or terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as to let the Enemy triumph over our Souls; though yet we muſt confeſs with Grief, that many Waters have gone over them. The ſwelling Torrents of ſinful Paſſions and Proſperity, the mighty Floods of worldly Cares and Vanities, the ſuperſluities of naughty ſenſual Pleaſures, have not only toſſed and endangered, but even overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ſwallowed up our Lives. So that we have been ſinking into deſtruction, like thoſe that are howling in the Pit.</p>
               <p>Alas! the bitter Streams of our vile imaginations and tranſgreſſions, have, like a deadly draught or Poyſon, been ſuck'd in greedily, and ſent to our very Hearts; ſo that we had been paſt all means of eſcape, or hope of ſuccour, if thou hadſt not ſtood by us, as thou didſt by thy Servant <hi>Paul,</hi> and not only ſtrengthened, but ſaved us, as thou didſt the Prophet, by drawing us forth as thou didſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the dangerous Gulph of eſtrangement and infidelity, into which our triple Enemies would have thrown us. Their Power would be great, like their Malice: Didſt not thou take our part, O holy Spirit! and plead our Cauſe. O ſweeteſt <hi>Jeſus!</hi> Bleſſed be thy omnipotent, and moſt glorious Mercy, that hath made our Souls as a Bird that may fly up to Heaven and be ſecure. We praiſe, and thank thee, deareſt Father! for thoſe Wings of Faith, Prayer, Love, and Devotion, whereby we can eſcape the Snare of the cunning Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and all his noyſom Plagues and Temptations. O! ſtill cover us, both with thy gracious Protection, and with the lovely Wings of the Holy of Holies, ſo that we may break the Bands of <hi>Satan</hi> aſunder, and caſt away his Cords from us, and neither have the Eyes of our Faith held from ſeeing thee, nor the Feet of our Affections from ſeeking thee, but like thy beloved and moſt loving Diſciples, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> leave our Nets whereby we take others, and all thoſe Entanglements where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are ſo caught our ſelves, and throw off every Impediment for the better, following of our Maſter <hi>Chriſt,</hi> under the Patronage of whoſe Love and Power we would rooſt and neſtle our Beings for ever: For it is he that hath made Heaven and Earth for us, for our Habitation, and will make a new Heaven and Earth about us for our Regeneration. And ſince this is a greater Bleſſing than the firſt Creation of Man, let our delivery from the Jaws of Hell bring him more Honour than all his other Dealings with us, even Glory for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:199576:21"/>
            <head>THE SIXTH Pſalmof Degrees, BEING The CXXV. <hi>PSALM,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Like the <hi>11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> Pſalm, ſheweth <hi>David</hi>'s Truſt and Recourſe to God, not like <hi>Saul</hi> to the Witch of <hi>Endor,</hi> or Wealth of <hi>Amalek,</hi> but where Believers are eſtabliſhed and ſecured in the Preſence of the Almighty, and perpetuity of the Church, whereby they find the goodneſs of their Portion, and the evil Lot of the Wicked, whatſoever he be, whether Hypocritical, Profane, or Backſliding.</p>
               <p>It is applied by the <hi>Rabbins</hi> to the Days of the <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> and ſo by us it may be appoſitely uſed on Sacramental Days, or any ſuch time of greater manifeſtation and experience of God's Integrity, and the Faith of Man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HO on the Lord do build their Truſt,<note place="margin">For S. <hi>John's</hi> day.</note> like <hi>Si╌on</hi> they command; up in╌to Heav'n their Heads they thruſt, their Feet un╌mo╌ved ſtand.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:199576:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Right ſafe, high, ſtrong, they always ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Like God's moſt Holy ground;</l>
                  <l>The Rock of Ages on each hand</l>
                  <l>Doth ſhade them, and ſurround.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As Hills <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſurround</l>
                  <l>To deck her, and defend;</l>
                  <l>So God encircles, and hath crown'd</l>
                  <l>His folk, World without end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As Hills, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For leaſt in Sin their Suff'rings end,</l>
                  <l>Though an <hi>Egyptian</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">For the Rod or Scepter of Wickedneſs is the Tyranny of a <hi>Pharaonick</hi> Oppreſſion over the lot of the Righteous, that is, the Church of God; which he may lay on, but will not leave, nor ſuffer to lye ſtill, God having the Rod of their Portion in his hand, (alluding to the old way of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition by Staves, whereof ſee <hi>Numb.</hi> 17. and <hi>Joſh.</hi> 18.) For the Reaſons mentioned ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how aptly the Portions of the Wicked (let them be never ſo fat or fair, like <hi>Eſau</hi>'s here) are termed Rods to plague oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times both themſelves and others, as <hi>Dives</hi>'s Portion did: But the Portion of the Godly is ſtiled a Lot, and a pleaſant one, as <hi>David</hi>'s 16 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. or a Cup of Bleſſing indeed, like <hi>Jacob</hi>'s; and of abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, like <hi>Benjamin</hi>'s, <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.11. <hi>Gen.</hi> 44.2.</note> Rod</l>
                  <l>To th' <hi>Goſhen</hi> of the good extend;</l>
                  <l>'Tis thence remov'd by God.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Do good ſtill to the Good, O Lord,</l>
                  <l>To him whoſe Heart and Line</l>
                  <l>Bend not to wrong; whoſe Feet ne're trod</l>
                  <l>Ways which to Hell encline.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since ſuch, as crooked ways encline</l>
                  <l>To do, or cheriſh ill,</l>
                  <l>God ſhall drive from him; but deſign</l>
                  <l>Peace to his <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For ſuch, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To Father, Son, and</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">The ſuddain change in the expreſſion of God, from the ſecond Perſon to the third: As it is an elegancy in the Original, ſo it may note, ſuch ſhall not know God (in the ſecond Perſon of the Trinity) as a Saviour, but at a far greater diſtance as a Judge; <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38, 39. who draw back, and turn aſide (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting their way which is already crooked, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.2.) to more depraved Obliquities, and deſperate Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, after a profeſſion of the right way: But they ſhall be tortured with Hypocrites and Unbelievers, while he ſhall be kept (like <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gen. 32.) in perfect Peace, whoſe Mind is ſtayed on God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.3. to the greater vexation of thoſe <hi>Edomites,</hi> who perhaps ſometime perſecuted him.</note> 
                     <hi>Ghoſt, we bow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One glorious God w' adore:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As in beginning was, is now,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſhall be evermore.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:199576:22"/>
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Sixth <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXV. PSALM.</head>
               <p>O Thou immutable Lord God, moſt faithful Creator, Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and Comforter, I deſire not only to believe of thee in the world, to credit what thou art in thy ſelf; but to truſt to what thou ſayeſt in thy Goſpel, to rely on thee for what thou doſt at preſent, and acquieſce in thee for what thou wilt do hereafter, and ſtay my ſelf on thee through thine everlaſting good pleaſure: For thou art the Lord that doſt not change, and therefore we are not conſumed, but are converted from Creatures to thy Children, confirmed from our weakneſſes by thy Spirit, and continued in thy ſervice with thy ſelf.</p>
               <p>Ah the ſafety! the aſſurance, the ſteadineſs, the ſolace, the ſole and ſupernatural ſatisfaction that is in fulneſs of Faith upon thee the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the Lamb of God, who makeſt us thereby the Temples of the living God, the City of the Lamb, the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that ſhall aſcend up above, and be made illuſtrious with all the Jewels of the concord, regularity, and brightneſs of Spiritual Graces, as with the eternal Riches of ineffable Love, and heavenly Glory: So that we ſhall never be removed from our Abode in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (thou haſt made our Rock ſo ſtrong), and if we believe ſurely we ſhall be eſtabliſh'd for ever, for the foundation of God ſtands ſure. As we ſhall here be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with the munition of Rocks, (the Rock of Ages, and all his Angels) like <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the holy City; ſo alſo we ſhall be wholly bleſt, and ſaved to the very uttermoſt: For neither the blaſts of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation (the Spirit that rules in the Children of Diſobedience) ſhall attack the corners of our Dwellings, as he did <hi>Job</hi>'s Sons; nor from the Wilderneſs aſſault us (as he did our Saviour) to ſpoil our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or our hopes. Nor ſhall the ſtorms of Tribulation be able to beat upon our Houſe, ſo as to make it ſhake or totter: For though our building of Faith be raiſed high, even unto the Heavens; yet it is no <hi>Babel,</hi> it is no <hi>Jericho,</hi> but a Fabrick that the Lord will bleſs and defend, and becauſe it ſtands upright, it ſhall ſtand faſt for ever. The ſtrength of our confidence in God ſhall put to flight the Armies of thoſe Aliens that would enter and deſtroy its ſtrong holds; for there are Mountains of Horſes, and Chariots of Fire, round about the Faithful to ſecure them; ſo that they cannot be immur'd or ſhut up, when never ſo cloſely begirt by Adverſaries. They can ſtill look up, nay, go up to the Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> from whence comes their help, even to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the Author and finiſher of their Faith, who not only pitched the forces of his Word and Miracles, but the red Standard of his Croſs,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199576:23"/>and the firſt Camp of his Martyrs and Apoſtles upon the Hills of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> to Convoy all Comers to the City of our God, and to draw all to him from the Center of the World.</p>
               <p>Oh therefore! let neither the Rod, nor the Staff of the Wicked, be laid or leſt upon my ſcore or part, leſt I do or ſuffer the evil of Sinners; but let thy Rod, and thy Shepherds Staff, both thy Croſs and mine, dear <hi>Jeſu,</hi> comfort and fill up my Cup, and make mine Heritage and Lot like thine: For then it ſhall be good, and thou that art ſo, ever wilt do good to me, making and keeping me upright in Heart, clean in my Hands, ſingle in mine Eye of Faith, and ſound in the Feet of mine Affections, ſteady in the ways of thy Commandments.</p>
               <p>Lord! if thy hand be not graciouſly (when moſt heavily) upon me, how ſoon may I put forth my hand unto wickedneſs, like <hi>Cam, Pharaoh, Balaam, Achan,</hi> and <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and like <hi>Judas, Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This makes me yet pray more earneſtly, that Chriſt may ſtill pray for me, ſince he that Chriſt prays for ſhall believe aright; and he that ſo believes, ſhall not find upon his lot the Scepter of Unrighteouſneſs, the Rule of Satan, the Domination of Sin, the Rod of the Wicked, the Guilt or Puniſhment of Reprobates.</p>
               <p>Oh then! that my lot and laſt end may be in the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Jeſus</hi> my Lord, that I may not fall preſumptuouſly, nor fear greatly, nor be driven forth with evil doers; but be led forth into the Paths of Peace into the ſtraight way that leads to life, there to taſte of the Brook in the way (the quiet and ſufficiency thou affordeſt thy Flock here) and to drink of the Rivers of thy Pleaſures hereafter; to lye down like thy Sheep in the green Paſtures of Hope, in the never fading, never failing encloſure of thine Arms, and to riſe in Glory with thine Inheritance for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:199576:23"/>
            <head>THE SEVENTH Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXXVI. <hi>PSALM,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Is thought to be compoſed by <hi>Eſdras,</hi> or ſome of that time, after the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Bondage, becauſe in the firſt part of the Pſalm it joyfully Celebrates the Return of ſome, as in the ſecond part heartily wiſhes the Reſtoration of all the reſt of the Captivity, from the Land of the North, (as the Realm of <hi>Babylon</hi> is called,<note place="margin">Jer. 13.19, 20. Jer. 16.19.</note> in regard of its ſite to <hi>Judea</hi>) making that apt and excellent reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of them to Strcams, running into the dry and deſolate parts of the South, which muſt needs be very welcome there, and are ſaid to flow thither as Torrents in great abundance, upon the melting of the Snows, and producing of Showers by the South Wind: So that whether you take נגב for the South Wind, or South part of the World, the compariſon may hold to either acceptation of the Word very full and elegant. The <hi>Jews</hi> flocking Southwards home, but (not all together) as the Spirit of God moved on the Waters in <hi>Babylon,</hi> in the Days of <hi>Cyrus, Darius,</hi> and <hi>Xerxes,</hi> ſtirring up <hi>Zerubbabel, Ezra, Nehemiah,</hi> and others, to bring back the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> reſtore Religion, rebuild the Temple, and repair <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which had been demoliſhed and burnt by <hi>Nebuzaradan</hi> in the fifth Month,<note place="margin">2 Kin. 25.8.</note> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) and in that ſame Month (about Harveſt time) was the Return of the <hi>Jews</hi> with <hi>Ezra, c. 7. v. 9.</hi> who had been led away Captive at their Sowing time: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Simile of the Husbandman here was rarely appoſite, both to the occaſion of their Joy, and ſeaſon of the Year, and their manner of Exaltation.</p>
               <p>This <hi>PSALM</hi> is very proper for our <hi>23<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                  </hi> of <hi>April,</hi> and <hi>29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> of <hi>May,</hi> or any ſuch happy Time of recovery from Trouble, Danger, and Oppreſſion.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:199576:24"/>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>FTER the long Night of a State, ſo dark as ours, ſo de╌ſo╌late; who could ſo much as Dream, that we ſhould wake out of Cap╌ti╌vi╌ty? But when God took that Plague a╌way, that <hi>E╌gypt</hi> which on <hi>Si╌on</hi> lay; our Pangs, like Dreams, a╌way did fly, and we had ſafe de╌li╌ve╌ry.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:199576:24"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pleas'd, and tranſported with our Change,</l>
                  <l>By a Recovery ſo ſtrange;</l>
                  <l>(As Cripples cur'd by Wonders) we<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 3.9.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Soon got both Strength and Liberty.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Soon we got well, well home; and found</l>
                  <l>Grief did no Soul, no Body wound:</l>
                  <l>But Hearts and Tongues in Pſalms agree,</l>
                  <l>And they got Feet as well as we.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then both our Chains and Silence broke;</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Pagans</hi> too, the Truth thus ſpoke:</l>
                  <l>The Lord hath done great things for ye;</l>
                  <l>The Lord hath done ſo, anſwer'd we.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therefore God's Works with joy we tell,</l>
                  <l>Which may convince the Infidel;</l>
                  <l>And call up Pray'rs for ſuch as be</l>
                  <l>Not yet return'd from Slavery.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O! were our Friends (our Foes and all)</l>
                  <l>Redeem'd from their <hi>Egyptian</hi> Thrall;</l>
                  <l>From Satan, and from Sin ſet free,</l>
                  <l>How welcome were their Liberty?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Welcom as <hi>Nilus</hi> in the South,</l>
                  <l>And ſweet as Show'rs in days of Drouth;</l>
                  <l>For all, with us, we long to ſee</l>
                  <l>Reap Mirth, who plough'd in Miſery.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sure, Lord, thy Lab'rers, in the heat</l>
                  <l>Who take the pains, ſhall taſt the Wheat;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.7, 8, 9.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And may with ſhouts receive from thee</l>
                  <l>A Largeſs of Proſperity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We, who dropt little hopes in Tears,</l>
                  <l>When driven hence by Foes or Fears;</l>
                  <l>Now loaded back with Solace, ſee</l>
                  <l>Rich Incomes from Captivity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus the poor Seeds-man ſadly goes,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eundo ibit, &amp; flendo port<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>s pretlum ſeml<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis: pretloſum ob caricaiem.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>While on the ground his Wealth he ſtrows;</l>
                  <l>But when the Harveſt Crowns him, he</l>
                  <l>Jogs home with Sheaves and jollity.<note place="margin">Veniendo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niet cum ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> sat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So they who ſhed a few ſmall Tears</l>
                  <l>I'th' Seed-time of their Hopes and Fears,</l>
                  <l>Shall glad Returns from Sadneſs ſee,</l>
                  <l>And ſhock up more Felicity.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:199576:25"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, he that goes from hence, and bears</l>
                  <l>To Earth his Duſt, to Heav'n his Tears;</l>
                  <l>Shall find thoſe precious Grains to be</l>
                  <l>Vaſt Crops in bleſt Eternity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In the Lord's Praiſe let none be dumb,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But Father, Son, and Ghoſt adore:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who was, and is, and is to come,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thrice Bleſſed God for evermore.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:199576:25"/>
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Seventh <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXVI. PSALM.</head>
               <p>O Moſt dear Redeemer <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who wouldeſt be the Lord our Righteouſneſs, we muſt confeſs thou mighteſt juſtly become our Enemy, (as <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren became his Foes) becauſe of the multitude of our Dreams; thoſe vain conceits of Happineſs which have been truſted and lean'd upon, though but <hi>Egy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptian</hi> Reeds, have greatly merited thy Puniſhment, and our farther deceptions. We have deſerved to be moſt terribly miſtaken, like the hungry wretch, who dreams he eats, but he awakes, and behold he is faint, and the more afamiſht. Thus are our Souls but the more ſtarved by thoſe Viſions of the Night; thoſe ſhort unſatisfying plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; thoſe ſhadows, and fond imaginations, in which we have been lull'd aſleep by the Fleſh, the World, and the Evil one, leading us Captive by them at their pleaſure. But, Lord, if thou wilt teach us like thy ſelf, to lead Captivity Captive, and to ſubdue their triple Band that lies in Ambuſh againſt us, (as <hi>Abimelech</hi>'s againſt the Men of <hi>Shechem</hi>) then ſhall we be like the Widow's Son raiſed even from the Dead: We ſhall not only recover our ſtrength wonderfully, as did the Cripple, before we go hence, but be recalled with <hi>Lazarus</hi> to newneſs of Life, and have our Wills and Faculties unbound, our Mouths and Hearts opened, our Hands and Feet looſed and enlarged to ſing the Praiſes of the Lord, to run the Paths of his Commands, and to teach Tranſgreſſors his ways, that ſo Sinners may be converted unto him, admiring the great things which God hath done for us, and we praiſe him for continually; for as God's Praiſe muſt be ever in our Mouths upon the account of his miraculous Redemption of us, (who were conquered and taken, enſlaved and ſold) ſo ought we inceſſantly to pray for the Converſion of others, (remembring thoſe that are in Bonds as bound with them) and that thy Servants, O Chriſt! who are many, may be made one Bread, and they who ſit in the darkneſs of Ignorance, or in the ſhadows of Error, may be delivered from the power of Satan, into the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed Lord! thou haſt Brethren here that the World knows not, nor thinks to be ſuch. O! that all the Sheep, though they have gone aſtray, may be reduced from their Wanderings, and brought out of their Wilderneſs, Condition, and deſert State, by reſting on the Shoulders of thy Power, and leaning on the Boſom of thy Love. O thou well-beloved and beſt loving <hi>Jeſus!</hi> how grateful, gracious, and deſirable, how profitable, ſweet, and ſuitable will ſuch a ſtream of Grace prove to thine <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their Pilgrimage? It will be a Well
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:199576:26"/>ſpringing up, and raiſing thy poor Creatures unto Life; it will be like drops upon the tender Herb, like ſhowers upon the thirſty Ground, making the hard-hearted and barren Soul to rejoyce, and to break forth into gladneſs, and into fruitfulneſs: For when thy Word diſtills like the Dew, and thou ſendeſt a gracious Rain upon thine Heritage, it muſt needs be refreſh'd and renew'd like the face of the good Ground which thou haſt Bleſs'd; for that which is ſterile is nigh unto Curſing, but that which kindly receives the Rain that comes oft upon it, brings forth Food meet for him by whom it is dreſſed, what kind of Husbandry ſoever he uſeth towards it. So we beſeech thee grant, O thou good Husbandman! that (ſince thou doſt ſo plentifully ſhower amongſt us thy benefits, and the good tidings of the Goſpel) we may bring forth the fruits of thy Spirit, ſuch as are proper for our places and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and for the Ages of our Lives, and of the World, what way ſoever thou takeſt with us, whether thou break us up by the Plough of Afflictions, or dig about us by forbearance and proſperities.</p>
               <p>We know that he who Sows the good Seed of thy Grace in an honeſt Heart with the Tears of true Remorſe (although the Enemy ſhould mingle Tares among the Wheat, yet) being a painful Labourer, ſhall Reap a good Crop at the Harveſt of the World, and that with Joy, and not with Grief; for godly Sorrow worketh Repentance unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, not to be repented of. Let us not therefore ſorrow, as do many, for Temporal loſſes, but rather let us rejoyce that thou poureſt down plentifully of thy Grace upon us, which is better than abundance of Corn and Wine. And ſo even when we go forth, with <hi>Peter,</hi> weeping bitterly for our Sins, if we bear with us the precious Seeds of Adoption and Regeneration; and theſe abide with us, although we may lye down in the duft of Death, or go out of the Land of the Living here, yet ſhall we come again with Boſoms full of Joy, and with Arms full of a <hi>Jeſus</hi> that went out before us bearing our Reproach, and who with Tears and ſtrong Cries pleaded for the handful that was given him out of the World, and ſhall come again like a happy Reaper, bringing Sheaves of Corn with him, that the people whom he hath laboured for, and united unto himſelf, may be crowned with Victory, Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Glory, and compleated with Gladneſs with him for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:199576:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE EIGHTH Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXXVII. <hi>PSALM,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Was compiled by <hi>Solomon,</hi> as a Compendium of his <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> ſhewing the vanity (and therein the vexation) of all worldly Travel and Care without God's Bleſſing, in the principal inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this Life's concernment, which are the building of our Houſes by ſtrength and ſafety, as in the firſt Verſe; by Fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Wealth, as in the ſecond Verſe; and chiefly by Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Heirs, to make our Habitations, Names, and Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances to remain for ever, as much as in us lieth, as in the third: And this I take to be the meaning here of building an Houſe, as it is the work of the Maſter of a Family in Oeconomy, rather than that of the <hi>Mathematician</hi> in Architecture: And in this ſenſe the Phraſe is taken oft in Scripture; as we read,<note place="margin">Exod. 1.21.</note> God gave the Midwives for their Faith, Hope, and Charity, Protection, Riches, and Progeny, to ſupport their Families: So likewiſe,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 17.10, 11.</note> the promiſe of God's building <hi>David</hi>'s Houſe, is explained by giving him Iſſue, which ſhould eſtabling his Kingdom botter than <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> could do, notwithſtanding all his Wiſdom, Power, and number of Women; ſince we read but of one Son (and he weak and infirm) which that mighty Builder raiſed up to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Royal State, Crown and Dignity of the Houſe of <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well then might the Author of this Pſalm (who hath inſerted his Name <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the ſecond Verſe) be a Type of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and begin to affirm and reiterate the <hi>Niſi Dominus</hi> here, and infer that, <hi>Except the Lord</hi> (<hi>David</hi>'s Lord, as well as Son) <hi>did build his Houſe,</hi> Solomon, <hi>and other Kings, ſhould but labour in vain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Pſalm might be ſuperſcribed with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as being ſung with loud and frequent Reſponſes by the <hi>Levites,</hi> at the erecting and re-edifying of the Temple, and therefore intended by me <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as an Anthem for the Day of a Nativity, or Baptiſm.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:199576:27"/>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>IL God the Houſe doth build,<note place="margin">For <hi>Shrove-Tueſday,</hi> or a Wedding.</note> and Fa╌mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maintain; Workmen, tho' ne're ſo ſtrong, or skill'd, La╌bour, a╌las! in vain. Fa╌thers get Sons in vain; in vain the Watchmen ward our Gates, un╌leſs the Lord or╌dain his Hoſt, to be our Guard.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:199576:27"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>In vain a Life we keep,</l>
                  <l>Riſe early, late take Reſt;</l>
                  <l>Fare hardly,<note place="margin">For I take it with the 72 <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, when others take pains with care to provide for their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, God's Beloved thrive better, and yet do not ſo much as loſe their ſleep, or reſt, in purſuit of thoſe enjoyments, which others inceſſantly toyl for. This ſhews the vanity of our Solicitude, as the other ſence (<hi>viz.</hi> ſo he gives) ſpeaks God's Bleſſing of honeſt Labour, whereby he brings Reſt, and makes both it, and what elſe got by Labour, pleaſant, according to <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.11.</note> loſe our loved Sleep,</l>
                  <l>'Till God our Stock hath bleſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But they, whom God hath bleſt,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Job,</hi> regain their Peace;</l>
                  <l>God gives his <hi>Jedidiahs</hi> Reſt,<note place="margin">Nempe Dile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis Domini, viz. <hi>Jedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diah's,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Solomon.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And with their Reſt; Encreaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Look,<note place="margin">All Children are given as an Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, paſſing from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to us, not purchaſed by our own Ability; but the Wiſe and Good are more than <hi>David</hi>'s plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and goodly Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; for they are alſo a Reward (as here) and a Crown, eſpecially ſuch as are born to us in our ſtronger and youthful Age; who may be grown up, and able to give advice and aſſiſtance, and ready at hand to help or adorn, as Arrows in the Quiver of an Archer; ſo that we may go in or out of the Gates of our Houſe, City, or Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, with honour and ſafety, and ſpeak either with Friends or Foes, ſtrong or great, the Judge or General. Whether it be in public in the ſight of all, (as <hi>Aben Ezra</hi> conſtrues <hi>in Portâ</hi>) or whether it be in the place where the People aſſemble, where the Nobles meet, where the Thrones are ſet, the Prophets prophecy, the Right is pleaded, the Guards are kept, the Soldiers ſtand, and the Judges fit, as they did formerly in the Gate. Vide <hi>Ruth</hi> 4.1. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.10. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 7. 20. <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.52. &amp;c.</note> ev'n our beſt Encreaſe,</l>
                  <l>Children come from the Lord;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ruth</hi> 4.13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe Fruits of th' Womb,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.2.</note> which ſome may gueſs</l>
                  <l>Man's Work, are God's Reward.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Children both give, and Ward</l>
                  <l>A blow; for (though but young)</l>
                  <l>To Parents they're a double Guard,</l>
                  <l>Like Weapons to the Strong.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe Shafts help againſt wrong,</l>
                  <l>Life againſt Death provide;</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s, they home are flung</l>
                  <l>To ſhield our threaten'd ſide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Happy the Man, whoſe ſide</l>
                  <l>Bears Quivers of ſuch Arms;</l>
                  <l>For whereſoe're his Cauſe is try'd,</l>
                  <l>He's quit of Shame and Harms.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:199576:28"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus we, whom God hath Bleſt,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Job,</hi> regain our Peace;</l>
                  <l>Since God gives his Beloved Reſt,</l>
                  <l>And with our Reſt encreaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>To God the Father, Son,</l>
                  <l>And God the Holy-Ghoſt,</l>
                  <l>Be Glory; and let every one</l>
                  <l>Strive who ſhall praiſe God moſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>HOSANNA.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:199576:28"/>
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Eighth <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXVII. PSALM.</head>
               <p>GRacious Father! who workeſt hitherto as thy Son alſo worketh, look upon us thy Workmanſhip, make us thy Building, who as lively Stones, well wrought and figured, would be built up a Spiritual Houſe unto thee: And we know, except thy Divine Wiſdom thus frame and raiſe us, bearing up the Pillars of our Strength, hewing out the Stones of our hard Hearts to be poliſhed Corners of thy Temple, we ſhall prove but ſorry Tabernacles, but fooliſh Builders, and Labourers in vain: For who amongſt us can ſay, that he hath made his Heart clean? Who can come to the Rock to lay a good Foundation, except it be given him from above? Or who can keep himſelf ſo clean, as that the foul and wicked Spirit touch him not, nor enter in again after he hath been caſt out of a Man, except thou, O Lord! who art ſtronger than the Enemy, doſt watch and defend the Houſe of the poor Soul? Thou muſt work all our Works in us, and for us, for without thee we can do nothing. O therefore! raiſe, ſtrengthen, ſtabliſh, and compleat us thou glorious <hi>Solomon,</hi> thou who muſt edifie us by thy Apoſtles and Teachers, and inſtruct us how to be Temples for thy holieſt Spirit, and the Heritage of the Lord for evermore.</p>
               <p>We muſt acknowledge that our beſt Skill, and carefulleſt Actions, our Watchings and Faſtings, our Righteouſneſs and Charities; are as Stones which thou, O Maſter Builder! mighteſt refuſe, being fit for nothing but to debaſe and throw us down to Hell, affording us no prop or ſafe reliance upon them. 'Tis thou alone, O trueſt <hi>Jedidiah!</hi> that foundeſt thy beloved Church upon the Corner-Stone of Faith, which edifies with joy and peace, with reſt and firmneſs in believing. So build us up, we beſeech thee, and watch over our Souls, that we may not be found to have watch'd, or to have work'd, to have inſtructed our Hearts, to have cleanſed our Hands in vain, but to have done the Work, and compleated the Task which thou haſt appointed us to do, by edifying both our ſelves and others in our moſt holy Faith. We throw our ſelves, Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> on thy gentleſt Boſom of Compaſſions, to be regarded and inſtructed by thee, and truſt that we are not <hi>Judas</hi>'s whilſt we eat of thy Bread, and drink of thy Cup, but ſhall be unto thee Sons and Daughters, ſuch an Inheritance as may be the Crown of thy Rejoycing, the purchſe of thy Labours, the proof of thy Power, the Arrows in thy Quiver, with which thou mayeſt triumphantly come to the Almighty, and ſay, <hi>Behold me, and the Children which thou haſt given me.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:199576:29"/>
               <p>Let not thine Arms be full or weary, dear Lord, 'till thou haſt enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our Souls within them, and made us ſo the Children of thy ſtrength, as that we may be able to come with boldneſs to the Throne of Grace, and neither be affrighted when we meet with our Enemies in the Gate of Death, nor when we ſhall ſpeak with our Accuſer, and our Judge, at the great Tribunal of the laſt day.</p>
               <p>From the various Proofs of thy tenderneſs over thy Flock, in giving them repoſe and comfort, and bleſt content, in the midſt of their hard fare, hard work, and harder want, O skilful Shepherd of our Souls, let us learn to caſt our Care upon thee for our protection and proviſion, for thy preſervation of our Perſons, and propagation of our Families; and if thou careſt for us, we need take no more care than <hi>Abraham</hi> did, for God will provide for us, for our Off-ſpring, for our chief Good, and for his Glory. The Lord ſhall build his <hi>David</hi> a Houſe, and he will be an exceeding great Reward (even above that of the Fruit of the Womb) unto his Friend <hi>Abraham,</hi> whoſe Children we are if we believe as he: <hi>Lord, we believe, help our unbelief,</hi> that we might not throw away our loved ſleep, much leſs our beſt beloved Souls, in carking after the things of this Life, whether they be Pleaſures, Profits, Power, Poſterity, Preferments, or vain Paſt-times; for what are theſe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of a Soul? But giving up our Souls, Eſtates, and Concernments, into the hands of a faithful Creator, who is able to keep them and us to the very uttermoſt, let us be preſerved not only in perfect Peace and Proſperity in this Life, but alſo in a happy and ſafe Repoſe even in Death it ſelf, when we expect to reſt from our Labours, and to ſleep in Jeſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:199576:29"/>
            <head>THE NINTH Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXXVIII. <hi>PSALM,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Is a Deſcription of the Felicities of ſuch Good Men, as fear the Lord, (that is, ſay the <hi>Rabbins</hi>) who ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do well; who walk in the ways of God, and are not only negatively good but poſitively; making their own hands miniſter to their Neceſſities, (as the Apoſtle did) knowing that he who will not labour ſhall not eat: But ſuch as labour honeſtly, (either to obtain a lively-hood and ſubſiſtance here, or a better Life hereafter) ſhall find the fruit of their Pains to be Peace and Plenty: Not the Apples of <hi>Sodom.</hi> or Cluſters of <hi>Gomorrah;</hi> but thoſe of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies Temporal, Spiritual, Eternal: Such as are here enumerated, from the <hi>2d.</hi> Verſe to the end, far better than by any other Poet.</p>
               <p>Amongſt which Bleſſings, (as to this World) the greateſt are eſteemed,<note place="margin">Vitam quae fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt Beatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Martial. <hi>lib. 10. Epig. 47.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> A Fruitful Meet Companion, neither barren in good Works, nor Off-ſpring: And therefore compared to a Vine; or becauſe (ſaith <hi>Kimchi</hi>) ſhe can live well and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully within Doors, and only deſires that her Branches may go abroad: As a Vine (ſaith he) will grow and flouriſh though rooted within a Houſe, ſo the ſpreading Limbes be carried into the Air.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Then a chearful Table decently repleniſht, with Legitimate, Pious, and Health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Children: Likened to <hi>Olive</hi> Plants, either becauſe they are hopeful, and flouriſhing, (as the <hi>Olive</hi> Tree is always green;) or uſeful and Ornamental, (as thoſe Trees are to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments in the Eaſt;) or Emblems of unfading Happineſs, (as <hi>Olive</hi> Branches were to Victors;) or not a ſhameful and ſpurious Off-ſpring: For it is reported of the <hi>Olive</hi> Stock, that it will nouriſh no Grafts, but of its own Kind.</p>
               <p>Theſe Bleſſings being deſcribed by two ſuch admirable ſweet Compariſons, (that ſtrive to chear and refreſh the Laborious and Proſperous Man) the Author breaks off his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe by a ſhort Epiphonema in the <hi>5th</hi> Ver. (but who the Author of this Pſalm was appears not) and then in the <hi>6th</hi> and <hi>7th</hi> Ver. goes on to pray for other Joys for the good Man, towards the compleating thoſe promis'd in the <hi>2.3.4.</hi> Verſes. Which indeed ſo fed, nay feaſted my eager Thoughts with that moſt excellent Scripture Abundance, expreſt by Corn and Oyl,<note place="margin">Judg. 9.9, 13.</note> (that which Chears and Honours God and Man) that I could not withhold from enlarging my delight in ruminating thus far upon it.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Like the fat <hi>Olive,</hi> and the fruitful <hi>Vine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Chearful to make Man's Heart, his Face to ſhine,</l>
                  <l>Are well bred Children, and fruitful Wife;</l>
                  <l>In this World's Paradiſe thoſe Trees of Life:</l>
                  <l>They wander not afar, but ſtill abide</l>
                  <l>By their own lucky Boards, or Houſe's fide:</l>
                  <l>At Home they Live and Thrive, fix and Encreaſe,</l>
                  <l>The Proſperous Signs of Plenty, Mirth, and Peace.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pax (ſeu Pacem) ſuper Iſrael,</hi> concludes the Pſalm, as the <hi>125.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſeems proper for a Wedding day, or any ſuch time of Feſtivity, and therefore uſed thus Solemnly to be Sung after the Captivity by the <hi>Levites,</hi> among the other Pſalms of Degrees: And it is intended by me for St. <hi>Lucy's</hi> day, and <hi>New-year's</hi> Tide.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:199576:30"/>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſt is the Man that fears the Lord, and walks in ways taught by God's word: while ſuch a <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Vice refrains, to Priſon Walls tho bound he be, he ſpreads like <hi>Egypt</hi>'s patient Tree, and bears more Fruit by wearing Chains.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:199576:30"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who e're thou art that fear'ſt the Lord,</l>
                  <l>Fearing to ſin in work or word,</l>
                  <l>Plenty, with Eaſe, ſhall crown thy Pain;</l>
                  <l>Thy Hands ſhall get Wealth that will laſt,</l>
                  <l>The Sweets of which thy Lips ſhall taſt,</l>
                  <l>Doubling, by reliſhing, thy Gain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy Wife ſhall, like a fruitful Vine,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ruth</hi> 4.11, 12.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Deck thy Houſe-ſide, as well as thine,</l>
                  <l>And ſee thine Off-ſpring ſhade thy Board;</l>
                  <l>As pleaſant Olive-Plants are ſet,</l>
                  <l>To grace and guard thee at thy Meat,</l>
                  <l>Thus art thou Bleſt that fear'ſt the Lord.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In Heav'n thrice happy ſhalt thou be,</l>
                  <l>As here below 'tis well with thee,</l>
                  <l>Thy Joys from <hi>Sion</hi> ſtill encreaſe;</l>
                  <l>Thine Age to three Deſcents ſhall ſee</l>
                  <l>Thine Iſſue fair, thy Nation free;</l>
                  <l>And (what is beſt) on <hi>Iſrael</hi> Peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As here below 'tis well with thee,</l>
                  <l>In Heav'n thrice happy ſhalt thou be,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Sion</hi>'s ſhal thy Joys encreaſe;</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt out-live one Age, to ſee</l>
                  <l>Good on thy Land and Family,</l>
                  <l>And (which is beſt) on <hi>Iſrael</hi> Peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Glory be to the Father, Son,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Holy-Ghoſt, the Three in One,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whoſe Deity we ſhall adore;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Since ev'ry Perſon of the Three</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For ever was, ſhall ever be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And is, God Bleſſed evermore.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Ninth <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXVIII. PSALM.</head>
               <p>O Moſt glorious and gracious Lord God, who art fit to be feared, and worthy to be loved, grant that I may not only ſerve thee out of <hi>filial</hi> Reverence, and ſenſe of Duty, but alſo and chiefly out of moſt paſſionate Affection and Delight, walking in thy ways as well as learning them, and doing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:199576:31"/>thy Will as well as knowing it, from a principle of entire and true Love, and of full and abſolute Choice. Grant that whether I am born unto Trouble and Care, or to eat and reap the Fruit of others Pains, both by my own and others Labours, my Repoſe may be after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards more ſweet and nouriſhing, and my Enjoyments more ſolid, as my Endeavours ſucceſsful, while I have Religion, though not Riches, and that which with <hi>Content is great Gain,</hi> notwithſtanding the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and loſs of worldly Treaſures.</p>
               <p>If I partake of the true Vine, and of the travel of his Soul, who was full as God, and made full as Man, that of his fulneſs we might receive and feaſt for evermore, then how well ſhall it be with me here? How much better hereafter? Come what can come I ſhall have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort enough in this World, and a Crown in the next: Nay, I ſhall be a Crown to my dear Bridegroom, a Glory to my Redeemer, as the wiſe Spouſe is to her Husband; for in this, good and true is the Word of the Lord which he hath ſpoken (not only in the Literal, but alſo in the Spiritual ſenſe) and ſo ſhall his Work be; as to the Head, ſo to the Members. He will make the Church <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Wife, and ſhe ſhall be a Vine as well as he, and ſo great a Bearer, as that ſhe hall cover and adorn all the ſides of his Houſe, and bring him cluſters of <hi>Eſhcol,</hi> Grapes of <hi>Sion,</hi> Loads of Comfort and Satisfactions, Tokens of Plenty and Delight, for having trodden the Wine Preſs alone.</p>
               <p>And then, O beloved Husbandman! when thou ſhalt viſit this Vine, and behold the Off-spring which thou haſt brought her with tranſports of Joy and Contentation, O! then look upon me and mine, and ſee us grafted into the right Olive, though we be ſprung from that which is wild by nature, that we may grow up as Plants of thy own planting, and flouriſh round about thy Table: For this hath God promiſed unto thee, O Chriſt! and we beſeech thee to make it good unto us, by making us thy Children. O Lord! how ſhould we praiſe, honour, and ſerve thee? Were we, like <hi>David,</hi> ſuch Olive Trees as might be fixed in thy Houſe, and framed into more holy Uſes, to be farther inſtrumental to thy Glory? Behold a greater than <hi>Solomon</hi> is here to make us fit to attend thy Oracles, and with the Cherubs to be near thy Mercy Seat. Dear God! prepare us for ſuch high places there, however thou cut and ſtrike us here, that we might be the better for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and wrought out of the World's glory, for our own, into thine, even by the beauty of Holineſs, that New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that comes down from above. Then ſhall we admire the good of Sanctity, and wiſh the good of thy People all the days of our life, and rejoyce in the happineſs of thy Choſen all the days of Eternity: For as we are Bleſt in ſerving thee out of thy Houſe and Sanctuary, ſo we hope to be Bleſſed with thee in thy holy Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> where we ſhall ſee the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Harveſt of all Ages, the eternal Happineſs of our Generations, and the never-fading Peace of thy choſen <hi>Iſrael. AMEN.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:199576:31"/>
            <head>THE TENTH Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXXIX. <hi>PSALM,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Is a Commemoration, not unlike that Solemn one, which every true <hi>Iſraelite</hi> was to make at the Offering of the Firſt-Fruits;<note place="margin">Deut. 26.35, 36, 37.</note> and Secondly, a Prognoſtication of the curſed End and Ruine of the Church her Enemies, from the Conſideration of the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Deliverance which God had wrought, and reiterated for his People a Juventute (both from theirs and the World's Infancy;) ſo that at length their Adverſaries, according to their Prayers, ſhall be but weak, few, like the Graſs on the Houſe top,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not growing up, there being formerly a Meter, or gatherer of Graſs (as we have now of Grain), moſt in faſhion about thoſe fertile Countries, where Graſs is of an exceſſive length even at this day, (as modern Travellers' affirm.)</note> that withers before it's pulling.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Zion</hi>'s Foes (ſaith <hi>Ezra,</hi> or whoſoever it was, who in his Time compiled this Prophetical Pſalm and Prayer) ſhall one Day be ſo inconſiderable, that as they ſhall have no Eulogies to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage their Growth or Harveſt, ſo they ſhall need no Weapon to cut them down; for they ſhall drop away ſhamefully of their own accord, without a <hi>Dominus Vobiſcum</hi> ſaid unto them:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.25. Iſa. 36.10.</note> For all they may ſay (though not of a Truth) what once a <hi>Sennacherib</hi> and a <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> falſly affirmed, That <hi>God is with us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quâ de causâ à me Selectus eſt hic Hymnus in Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium</hi> Septembris. <hi>Propter</hi> M. O. C. <hi>nee non in Quintum</hi> Novembris.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:199576:32"/>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F <hi>Ja╌cob</hi> did in <hi>E╌gypt</hi> tell, what Troubles in his time be╌fell; how few and e╌vil were his Days? How hard Life's travel in rough ways: In <hi>Ca╌naan</hi> well may <hi>Iſ╌rael</hi> ſay, From my Youth up, God was my ſtay.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:199576:32"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>From my Youth up I met with Foes,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.16, 17.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But to God's Houſe I 'ſcap'd from thoſe;</l>
                  <l>Many a time was I aſſail'd,</l>
                  <l>But I as many times prevail'd:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>God broke my Cords which they did bind,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.24.25.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And made them Captive, if not kind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Long did they with deep Furrows wound,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.19.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And Plow my Back, as 'twere their Ground;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mark</hi> 15.15.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But the good Husbandman now cracks</l>
                  <l>The Ploughman's Whip on their own Backs:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>John</hi> 15.1.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Righteous Lord ſtays not too long<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>From reſc'uing his who ſuffer wrong.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therefore ſhall <hi>Zion</hi>'s Enemy<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.33.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Like Fools wax faint, like Cowards fly;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.6.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whom Pride doth cloath, Shame ſhall confound,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.18.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>As Corn that grows in no good Ground:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.5.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ſtands (with Kings) on the Houſe-Top,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where comes a Blaſt, and that's its Crop.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.30, 31.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Its Crop doth rot before 'tis ripe,</l>
                  <l>Nor can it fill the Reapers gripe,</l>
                  <l>Nor joy his Heart: For (what is worſe)</l>
                  <l>It bears no Burthen, but a Curſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis no Man's comfort, no Man's care;</l>
                  <l>No Man for ſuch bids one ſhort Pray'r.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:199576:33"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>None in God's Name give ſuch good ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Boaz</hi> to his Harveſt did:<note place="margin">Ruth. 2.4.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>[Gloria Patri.]</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But we to God will Glory give,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who, with the Son, and Spirit, doth live:</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>God Reigns, and ſhall, as heretofore;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bleſs'd be his Name for evermore.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:199576:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Tenth <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXIX. PSALM.</head>
               <p>O Deareſt <hi>Jeſu!</hi> let me behold thee as an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> indeed, in whom <hi>there was no guile,</hi> and yet how many a time, even from <hi>Herod</hi>'s perſecution of thee in thy Youth, wert thou afflicted. Thou didſt grow up as a Stem out of a dry Ground, very poorly and deſpicably in the Eyes of the vain proud World, who looked for another appearance and attendance than thou, O King of Glory! didſt affect on Earth, and therefore wert thou rejected as a Man of Sadneſs. And well mighteſt thou be acquainted with much Grief, when thou didſt bear our greateſt Sins, even thoſe whereby we did ſet thee at nought, (as did <hi>Herod</hi> and his Soldiers) and even ſought the holy Child, the Firſt-born of Grace, in our Hearts to take away its Life.</p>
               <p>O Lord! we muſt confeſs how many a time, too often, we have betrayed and expoſed thy Name and Body, thy Word and Members, to Shame and Reproach, to Indignities and Sufferings: We have ſmitten and pierced them through with many Sorrows; we have knotted the Whip, and lengthen'd out the Rods to plough thy Back, (as the <hi>Jews</hi> did by their laſhing Taunts when thou wert dying on the Croſs) only to non-plus thy Love and patience if it were poſſible: But the Lord is Righteous, and the Lord is Merciful, and therefore he hath cut aſunder the Cords of the Wicked, and by his Righteouſneſs ſhall juſtifie many, as alſo confound all ſuch as have evil will towards his <hi>Zion.</hi> Grant therefore, dear Lord! that we may not prove ſuch a Crop as grows upon the Houſe, or among the Stones, which withereth as ſoon as it is put forth. But as from our Childoood, we have been acquainted graciouſly with thy Mind and Goſpel, ſo grant that we may grow up in Grace, and in the knowledge of a Saviour, and have the Bleſſing of Almighty God from the very Ground of our Hearts, to the laſt Harveſt of our Lives, and be able to bleſs many others, as <hi>Boaz</hi> did, in the Name of thee,</p>
               <p>Our Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>TO thee, dear God! be all the Dominion, the Power and Glory of my Being, for thou haſt prepared it from the fury of my Adverſaries ever ſince the firſt motions of that evil Figment in my Heart, which hath broke out often into evil Concupiſcences, and endeavoured to plough with my Heifer, to plot with my naughty Fleſh, to bind and to deliver me a Priſoner unto Satan; but my Luſts have not led me Captive, nor plough'd upon my Back as they conſpired to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:199576:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>do, for thou, O Lord moſt juſt and holy! wouldeſt not ſuffer them to Tyrannize or Triumph too long over me, but haſt broke thoſe Bands of Wickedneſs, and caſt their Cords from me, that I might be thy Servant, and there the Lord my Righteouſneſs: So that I truſt they ſhall be confounded that contend with thee for my Soul, and I ſhall not be aſhamed while I wait on thee, though my Fleſh be as Graſs that withers away. Thou art my Strength, O Lord, and my Portion for ever, who wilt, I truſt, give a Bleſſing to my Seed, to my Harveſt, to my Houſe, to my Endeavours and Encreaſe, that my Work and thine may proſper in my hand, and bring fulneſs of Joy and Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to my Breaſt, while all the vain Thoughts, and viler Suggeſtions of my Heart, I deſire ſo to hate, as to wiſh (like the Graſs upon the Houſe tops withered and faded away) that they may never grow up to a Crop, leſt (ſowing the Wind) I Reap the Whirlwind, and have my Recompence in vanity (according to my delight or truſt,) and come to nothing before my time. But, O Lord! I wait on thee for a Bleſſing in this my day, and for thine Eternity, that I may be like a Field whom God hath enriched; if he be not on my ſide, I cannot proſper, and I know, him whom thou bleſſeſt is Bleſſed: <hi>Bleſs me therefore, even me, O!</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:199576:34"/>
            <head>THE ELEVENTH Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXXX. <hi>PSALM</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>De dolore Profundo, &amp; ex imo corde;</hi> and not (as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> would have it) <hi>De Profundis Purgatorii,</hi> to be uſed for the Dead: It is an Act and incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Hope, under the moſt weighty Preſſures, from this Proof, <hi>viz.</hi> That neither with the ſtrongeſt Angels, nor Saints departed, (much leſs with the greateſt, or beſt of Men upon Earth) is any Pardon or Propitiation to be found, but only with God; who alloweth us here ſpace and place for Repentance, that he may be feared, (not ſo ſlaviſhly as to be fled from, or hated) that he may be ſued unto, adored, and attended on, in the holy Duties of Prayer, Praiſe, and Truſt; which are comprized in this Pſalm to be uſed ſedulouſly and conſtantly night and day, according to that which the Repetition of the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon in the ſixth Verſe doth infer, which is thus gloſs'd on by Kimchi: <hi>My Soul waiteth in the Night for the Lord, that it may be in the number of thoſe who riſe in the Morning-Watch to pray.</hi> And this ſenſe being moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive of the Times and Method, both of <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> and the greateſt of Devotion, I follow it in my Verſion, and deſire to do ſo in my Practice.</p>
               <p>This Pſalm was made (as ſome think) in the time of the Captivity, for Redemption from it, as may be judged by the laſt Verſe: But others aſcribe it to <hi>David,</hi> giving it the ſame Date with the <hi>51<hi rend="sup">st</hi>,</hi> and is reckon'd the ſixth of the Penitentials, <hi>i. e.</hi> of thoſe which were uſed when public Penitents were brought and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to the Church, who might well ſay, <hi>Becauſe there is Pardon</hi> (as ſaith the Text) <hi>or Propitiation</hi> (as the <hi>72<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                  </hi>) with thee,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:199576:35"/>
                  <hi>O Lord, therefore ſhalt thou be feared,</hi> i. e. <hi>obeyed;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe the mildneſs of his Laws, and meekneſs of his Dealings, were ſtrong Motives for Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anthema Hócce à me uſitatum eſt, ut primò factum, in Secundum</hi> Octobris.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UT of the Deep, wherein, like <hi>Jo╌nas,</hi> I was try'd; out of the mire of Sin, my Clay to God hath cry'd, Lord hear my Voice, give what I crave; O! let me have thy Love, Heav'ns Joys.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:199576:35"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Too oft we chuſe falſe Joys;</l>
                  <l>And ſhould'ſt thou be ſevere</l>
                  <l>To chaſten our ill Choice,</l>
                  <l>What Man his Ills can bear?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But we have prov'd,</l>
                  <l>That thou may'ſt be</l>
                  <l>Pardon's with thee;</l>
                  <l>Both fear'd and lov'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I'le fear, leſt thou art lov'd</l>
                  <l>Too little; and I'le flee</l>
                  <l>(When Fear my Heart hath mov'd)</l>
                  <l>Unto thy Sanctuary:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Early and late</l>
                  <l>Grace to afford;</l>
                  <l>There waits the Lord,</l>
                  <l>Therefore I'le wait.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Soul on high ſhall wait,</l>
                  <l>(Like thoſe, who watch the riſe</l>
                  <l>Of Day) to Officiate</l>
                  <l>At Morning Sacrifice.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, like the Guard;</l>
                  <l>Remove the Night,</l>
                  <l>Who long 'till Light</l>
                  <l>And them reward.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Till <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Star reward</l>
                  <l>Your Hopes, and on you riſe;</l>
                  <l>Wait <hi>Iſr'el</hi> on your Lord</l>
                  <l>With wakeful wiſhing Eyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Look 'till the Sun</l>
                  <l>Doth heal and bleſs,</l>
                  <l>Of Righteouſneſs</l>
                  <l>And brings God's Son.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O! ſhield ye with his Sun</l>
                  <l>God's People, truſt his Word;</l>
                  <l>Since full Salvation</l>
                  <l>Attends our gracious Lord:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There's Pity ſeen,</l>
                  <l>Who will Redeem</l>
                  <l>And Pow'r in him,</l>
                  <l>Us from all Sin.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:199576:36"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Glory be to our King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who ſhall be, was, and is;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Loud Hallelujahs Sing</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To God, the God of Peace.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Lord of Hoſts,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Father, Son,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Three in One,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Holy-Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:199576:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Eleventh <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXX. PSALM.</head>
               <p>O Deareſt <hi>Jeſu!</hi> when I conſider thee, crying with ſtrong Cries to thy Father for me out of the depths of thine Agony, and of thy Sufferings, both in <hi>Gethſemane,</hi> and in <hi>Golgotha,</hi> how am I ſwallowed up in the Abyſſes, both of thy Paſſion and Compaſſion for us! Ah! what fathomleſs Depths indeed! O! what unmeaſurable Dimenſions, both of Grief and Goodneſs, are there for us to be immerſed in! and ſince they who are converſant among great Waters ſee the Wonders of the Lord, O! how may we behold theſe in the drops of thine Eyes, and of thy Wounds, in the Rivers of thy Tears, and of thy wonderful Sweat, in the Ocean of thy Love and Sorrows for Mankind! When thy Soul was heavy, and ſunk down even unto Death, and all the Cataracts of Shame and Fury paſſed over thy Head, O King of Righteouſneſs and Glory! yet out of the deep and horrible Pit of God's Wrath, into which thy condition was plunged for our ſakes, how didſt thou reach up thy very Sighs and Groans, thy Pains and Sadneſs, thy Prayers, and all thy Paſſions, unto Heaven it ſelf, to reach us thence a Medicine, and a Remedy, more certain Health, and a more happy Life, than the lifting up of the Serpent in the Wilderneſs ever brought to its beholders! I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore look unto thee, and be enlighten'd, even while thou ſeemeſt Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; I will ſtay my ſelf on the Tree of thy Croſs, and ſecure my ſelf under the Shadows of thy Crucifixion, when I am moſt caſt down or overwhelmed with the Seas of my Anxieties and Trials, for the Lord hath been deeply ſenſible of our Infirmities, and touched to the quick with humane Miſeries, that he might not be fled from, (as he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, both while he ſtood on <hi>Sinai,</hi> and on <hi>Golgotha</hi>) but that he might be feared, and approached unto with Reverence, becauſe there is a Propitiation with him for us, there is an Attonement made by him our High-Prieſt: Therefore, O God! hear my Voice, though my Sins cry aloud for Vengeance; and thou mayſt be more ſtrict (than thou wert formerly under the more imperfect Light of Nature, or of the <hi>Ieiſh</hi> Law) to mark the failings and ſtumblings of Mankind now in the lightſom day-time of the Goſpel; yet do thou, my Father,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jeremiah.</hi> 38.12, 13.</note> and my Prince, pity me in the Dungeon of my Corruptions, and draw my Feet out of the Mire of my Luſts, out of the Clay of my earthly Mindedneſs, out of the Waters of my worldly Sorrows, and bring me to the deſired Shore of thy ſure Mercies in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> ſet my feet on the Rock, and order my Goings, that my Foot-ſteps may not ſlip, but that I may walk in the Land of the Living unto the Land of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:199576:37"/>Promiſe; and when I go down to the bottom of the Mountains, and the Weeds are wrapt about my Head,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jonas.</hi> 2.5, 6</note> and the Earth with her Bars encloſe me on every ſide, that then I may not be caſt out of thy ſight, nor into the Bonds of mine Iniquities, nor into the Belly of the loweſt Hell: O our Father! ſince thou haſt not left thy Son there, grant that my Life may be brought up from Corruption. I know Salvation is from thee alone, and with thee infinite abundance of Bowels of the tendereſt Compaſſions why thou ſhouldeſt be reverenced and repaired unto, there is a <hi>Jeſus</hi> in thy Boſom to redeem from all Sins, from Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Enemies, and Troubles, and to repreſent us cover'd with his Righteouſneſs; otherwiſe ſhouldeſt thou view us in our Original Nakedneſs, or actual Filthineſs, we could not ſtand before thee in Judgment. But ſince there is Forgiveneſs with thee, O God! there is cauſe enough why we ſhould fly unto thee, truſt in thee, wait on thee, and watch for thee, more than they who watch for the Morning, for if Light be ſo grateful to thoſe who walk in Darkneſs, how amiable is thy Countenance to us in the gloomineſs of this preſent State? And how much more lovely will it be when we lie down in the Night of Death, that <hi>the Day-ſpring from on high</hi> may viſit us, and bring the joyful Morning of a Reſurrection, both from Sin and the Grave? O! do thou make haſt my beloved Saviour, and be <hi>as a Roe, and a young Hart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caut.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>on the Mountain of Spices:</hi> Thou that art the Hart of the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, who out of the midſt of thy deepeſt Woes, and dying Pangs, didſt cry unto God for us, do thou ſend us timely help, for we would ſeek thee early in the prime of our Age, (haſtening from the very dawn of our Lives to prevent the Night-Watches, and like thy Spouſe or beloved <hi>Mary</hi>) to ſee the Sun of Righteouſneſs riſen on the Earth before we get to our <hi>Zoar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O! that our Prayers might aſcend like Incenſe by the meritorious lifting up of thy Body for us! Dear Lord! impute no Guilt to us, but cleanſe us from all, that we may be bleſſed, and holy, and happy, as we beg to be, for thy own ſake, O gracious Saviour! to whom be Glory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:199576:37"/>
            <head>THE TWELFTH Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXXXI. <hi>PSALM,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Was compoſed by <hi>David</hi> in the life-time of <hi>Saul,</hi> when moſt humble, innocent, and diſtant from the Succeſſion to the Crown, though then ſuſpected, envied, and accuſed: It was appointed to be uſed at the <hi>Jews</hi> Return, becauſe no temper better qualifies us for God's Mercy, nor more becomes us under the greateſt Mercies, (ſuch as thoſe we have enjoyed) than that Humility, Self-denial, Reſignation, and Affiance in God's Will, which are here exemplified in the firſt and ſecond Verſes, and exhorted unto in the laſt.</p>
               <p>While the Pſalmiſt with that frequent Elegancy in the holy Tongue, ſuppreſſeth the Imprecation, and impoſeth a kind of Silence upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf after his Atteſtation, proceeding to an Aſſeveration, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>If I have not,</hi> &amp;c. viz. <hi>ſtill'd and pacifi'd my Soul as the Waves, Ievell'd and ſmooth'd my Brow like the face of the Ground, and have put my Hand upon my Mouth;</hi> viz. <hi>I have ceaſed from crying and throbbing, as at the Mother's command the Child doth, who although weaned, can without Sollicitude yield and conform to the Mother's Direction and Proviſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the Compariſon is fitly ſquared, As a Child is in quiet and order with its Mother, ſo is my Soul with me: (As the <hi>Jewiſh, Arab.</hi> notes the Repetition to import) <hi>I have weaned it from Tranſgreſſions: Non arrogavi mihi magna, mirabilia, inconceſſa, inhoneſta,</hi> as the firſt Verſe intimates; and this whole Pſalm, ſaith <hi>Grotius,</hi> ſavours much of a Goſpel Spirit, as of that gracious and modeſt Diſpoſition with which <hi>David</hi> was endowed, eminently, ſo as to make him be ſtiled, <hi>After God's own Heart.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:199576:38"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O,<note place="margin">For <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents</hi> day.</note> Lord! I do not look too high, tho to this lof╌ty pitch I fly, to ſeek thy Throne and Ma╌je╌ſty. No Earthly Crown do I de╌ſign, nor as my Sov'raign's Son to ſhine; my ſole Am╌bi╌tion's to be thine.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:199576:38"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>(Like <hi>Bethſhemites</hi>) I dare not pry</l>
                  <l>In things for me too Great, too High;</l>
                  <l>My Heart is humble as mine Eye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But the proud Foe my Heart miſtook,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt I his Frowns did fairly brook,</l>
                  <l>Without returning one Ill look.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſoon lay quiet, to control</l>
                  <l>The froward Paſſions, that did roll</l>
                  <l>Like Waves, about to move my Soul.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Soul is huſh't; like a wean'd Child,</l>
                  <l>That from the Mother's ſight exil'd,</l>
                  <l>To any thing's ſtrait reconcil'd:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſurely I my ſelf behave</l>
                  <l>Like a wiſe Man, while thus I crave</l>
                  <l>Like a weak Child, what I would have.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>May <hi>Iſr'el</hi> do, as I have done,</l>
                  <l>(To all things here indiff'rent grown)</l>
                  <l>Truſt always — But in <hi>God alone.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>May <hi>Iſr'el</hi> do, as we, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Give Glory, Praiſe, Dominion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To God the Father, with the Son,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Spirit, thrice Bleſs'd Three in One.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Sicut erat in Principio, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Now let us all the Lord adore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who is the ſame as heretofore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſhall be King for evermore.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>HOSANNA.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:199576:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Another VERSION of Pſalm CXXXI.</head>
               <head type="sub">[<hi>To be ſung as Mr.</hi> George Sandys <hi>Paraphraſe,</hi> Pſal. 1.]</head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ORD,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.21, 22. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.22.</note> I'le prelude to my Lord's humbleſt part,</l>
               <l>That I may be the Man <hi>after thine Heart;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I hate proud Looks, and glance not up an Eye</l>
               <l>At things too hard, too hidden, or too high.</l>
               <l>But as a Child, whom its kind Mother weans,</l>
               <l>(Loving the Breaſt) yet on her Boſom leans,</l>
               <l>I hold me at thy Hand; nor once repine,</l>
               <l>But quietly repoſe, receive, reſign:</l>
               <l>Wiſhing our <hi>Iſr'el</hi> thus may truſt God ſtill,</l>
               <l>And frame their State according to thy Will.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:199576:39"/>
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Twelfth <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXXI. PSALM.</head>
               <p>O Thou Son of <hi>David!</hi> of whom we ought to learn to be <hi>Meek and Lowly,</hi> let us ſee what kind of Diſciples we are by regarding our dear Maſter, and find what Proficients in thy School by minding the Copy thou haſt ſet us: There appeared not the leaſt glance of Pride, Arrogance, or Self-love, in thy Behaviour; there was not the leaſt Root of Bitterneſs in thy Breaſt, for thou cameſt to Attone the firſt Sin of our firſt Parents; and ſo for all thou wert exalted far above all that are here called Gods, yet thy Spirit was not haughty (as <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s) nor thine Eyes lift up to the forbidden Fruit.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 13, 32.</note> Thou wert willing to be ignorant (as Man) of thoſe things which did not befit Men to pry nicely into, that thou mighteſt ſtoop to the weakneſſes of thy Body the Church, and comply more abſolutely with the divine Will, and Compaſſionate more ſeriſibly the Infirmities or Ignorances of Mankind. O moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious condeſcending <hi>Jeſus!</hi> how were thy Delights among the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Men! while thou didſt not behave thy ſelf like a <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> like an Impoſtor that would be admired for ſome God below; but, like thy Servant <hi>Moſes,</hi> didſt vail thy ſelf, that thou mighteſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed withall, and didſt not walk too much obſcured by thine own Luſtre and Tranſcendency, but didſt leave the Doctors and Learned <hi>Jews</hi> to go down with thy humble Mother into <hi>Galilee,</hi> and to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto her as a weaned Child. And though thou wouldeſt not exerciſe thy ſelf in things too high for thee, yet, O! how low wouldeſt thou appear in thy Employments? How plain in thy Countenance? how eaſie and affable in thy Converſation? that Publicans and Sinners, and little Children, might come unto thee, and hear thy excellent Diſcourſes, and taſte thy miraculous Proviſions, while thou wenteſt about doing good, and telling Men that they ſhould follow thy ſteps in being meek, humble, quiet, and contented, doing Good, readily ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Evil patiently as dear Children.</p>
               <p>Lord! How then ſhould we abhor our ſelves, when we either think of thee, or of our ſelves! How unlike are we become to thee, if we claim any Kindred with thee! For do we not ſtill continue, like <hi>Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> among the Sons of Pride? Do we ſeem little in our own Eyes, as thy Servant <hi>David</hi> did, when thou didſt make him a great King? Or rather do we not lift up our Wills and Underſtandings, and walk with a ſtiff Neck of Perverſneſs in oppoſition to thee, as it were, aiming even at Heaven it ſelf, like the Tail of the old Serpent? So far are we from receiving the Kingdom of Heaven like little Children!
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:199576:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>But, O! when then ſhall it once be that we ſhall not be High-minded, but fear, and love, and own thee to be Lord over us? Then ſhall we not raſhly venture with <hi>Uzzah</hi> to meddle with thoſe things which are unmeet for us, or forbidden to us; but we ſhall be weaned from our Mother Earth, from the love of this dirty World, and from loving its foul Inclinations; and we ſhall caſt our Cares and Affairs on thee, renouncing all Self-Truſts or Conceits, to level the face of our Souls before the feet of the holy <hi>Jeſus;</hi> that when thou comeſt, O moſt holy Spirit! to <hi>prepare the way of the Lord</hi> in us, he may find no Rock nor Mountain, nothing too hard or haughty in us, nothing untractable or inacceſſible to obſtruct or oppoſe his Progreſs. But, O! let the too mighty Elevations of my vain Thoughts be brought down, and the crooked ways of my Heart be made ſtrait, and the rough ways of my Condition be made ſmooth, that my Soul may be ſtill quiet with me, and ſtill'd and quietted by thee. Rebuke the tempeſtuous Motions of a froward Mind, that I may repoſe my ſelf ſweetly and ſafely on thy Promiſes, on thy Proviſions, and reſign my ſelf wholly to thy Inſpirations: And God grant that all thine <hi>Iſrael</hi> may (like <hi>Jacob</hi>) wraſtle with Principalities and Powers, even in the higheſt and moſt heavenly Things; and though never ſo much in a Night of Cares and darkeſt perplexities, or to encounter with enraged Enemies, yet let them wait and hope on the Lord, and ſtay and ſtrengthen themſelves on their God (as <hi>David</hi> did at <hi>Ziklag,</hi>) for he is a ſure Reward, and a conſtant Reward, a Pillar of Fire, and a Pillar of a Cloud, a Sun, and a Shield, in whoſe Name we ought to truſt, denying our own Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, Affections, and Deſires, rather than an abſolute Dependance on him for ever and ever. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:199576:40"/>
            <head>THE THIRTEENTH Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXXXII. <hi>PSALM,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Is a Narration of <hi>David</hi>'s Devotion, and of God's Promiſes and Appointment; as to <hi>David</hi> and his Seed, and the ſetling of the Ark on <hi>Sion;</hi> which was a Type of the ſtability of Chriſt's Kingdom, and of the future Felicities of his Servants, in the Reign of the Son of <hi>David,</hi> (the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the Horn ſpoken of here in Verſe <hi>17,</hi> as the <hi>Rabbins</hi> agree) which the Apoſtle proves, <hi>Acts 2.30.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore it was ſolemnly uſed at the Rebuilding of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 6.41, 42. Deut. 12.11. 1 Chron. 17.11, 12.</note> and moſt probably (as <hi>Grotius</hi> thinks) a compoſition of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s at his raiſing of the Temple for the Honour of God, and the Place; containing in it part of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Prayer, part of God's Promiſe to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and to <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Kimchi</hi> and others think it made by <hi>David,</hi> at that very time,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 21.26. 1 Chron. 22.1.</note> when the ſcituation of the future Temple was mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly ſhewn unto him (as it is hinted in the word <hi>Invenimus</hi>) by the Sign from Heaven.</p>
               <p>For as <hi>David</hi> was abſolutely forbidden the building of a Temple, ſo 'till the Prophet <hi>Gad</hi> came to him with a Divine Command,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 17.12.</note> 
                  <hi>That he ſhould build an Altar in the Threſhing-Floor of Araunah:</hi> (For all his great deſire, like <hi>Abraham</hi>'s, to ſee ſuch a glorious Day, and notwithſtanding his Devotion, like <hi>Jacob,</hi> to the Service of God) yet he knew not the place that God would chuſe, as his Heaven upon Earth, for his moſt eminent and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:199576:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuitable Habitation. Therefore his Care and Concern chiefly refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting on his Vows here made were the more conſiderable, and might well be ſtiled <hi>Afflictions,</hi> worthy to be Commemorated as well as his former Perſecutions. His conſtant Humility, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, pious Sollicitude, and Affection for God's Service, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated in <hi>2 Sam. 7.2.</hi> and <hi>1 Chron. 17.16.</hi> and all theſe ſenſes the word <hi>Afflictions</hi> will bear, as I have ſhewn in my Verſion.</p>
               <p>Where alſo I have endeavoured to be as clear as I could in the Expoſition of that dark place of the ſixth Verſe,<note place="margin">Hic verſus plurimum Hebraeos fatigat. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit clarius.</note> which by ſome Commentators (like the <hi>Jewiſh Arab.</hi> here) is render'd much more ſhady and obſcure; ſo that the Elegant <hi>Caſtalio</hi> was forced to confeſs, That he underſtood not the meaning of the Text, <hi>viz.</hi> Verſe <hi>6.</hi> Therefore herein (as all along) by the help of the Crities, with the aſſiſtance of the Learned <hi>Hammond</hi> and <hi>De Muys,</hi> I ſtrive to ſum up briefly as much of the ſenſe as my Verſe and Knowledge will give me leave to do.</p>
               <p>Yet I cannot omit <hi>Buchanan</hi>'s Verſion of this hard Sentence, which is as ſingular, as his Paraphraſe elſewhere is excellent.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Fama licet Patriae multum promitteret orae,</l>
                     <l>Inter ſaxa tamen Sylveſtribus obſita dumis:</l>
                     <l>Monſtravit Deus ipſe locum, Deus ipſe perenne</l>
                     <l>Hic Templum; Templique ſacris ſedem innuitarie</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though Fame hath promis'd much to <hi>Judah</hi>'s Coaſt</l>
                     <l>By the Ark's ſtay, (whereof our Towns may boaſt;)</l>
                     <l>Yet God himſelf hath ſhown, and we have found</l>
                     <l>Old Prophecies, (which did at <hi>Bethlem</hi> ſound,</l>
                     <l>Fulfill'd on woody Hills. —</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>— where the Ark ſtood,</l>
                     <l>Or where it was to ſtand, high as a Wood.)</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>For the Woods of the Field, or the Fields of the Wood, may be taken as for the Houſe of <hi>Aminadab</hi> in the Hill of <hi>Kiriath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jarim,</hi> which was a City in a woody place, from whence <hi>David</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:199576:41"/>and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> fetch'd the Ark from the Houſe of <hi>Obed-Edom:</hi> So for the City of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and eſpecially the Mount <hi>Moriah,</hi> which was a cloſe Covert in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s time, witneſs the Ram caught in the Thicket; and was afterwards more adorned with Wood when the Temple was built thereon: This being frequently by the Prophets called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Wood;</hi> as <hi>Bethlechem,</hi> the place of Bread, is alſo called <hi>Ephratah,</hi> viz. <hi>Fruitful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was the City of <hi>David,</hi> where he might learn from his pious Anceſtors, that neither <hi>Silo,</hi> nor <hi>Gibeon,</hi> nor <hi>Nob,</hi> but <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah,</hi> (which was a part of Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and here by way of Eminency bears the name of the whole Hill) ſhould be the chief place of worſhipping the <hi>Mighty God of Jacob.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God is ſo called here, becauſe he calls himſelf the <hi>Almighty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 35.10, 11. Gen. 49.24. Gen. 28.20.</note> when he named <hi>Jacob, Iſrael;</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> firſt calls God ſo, and is the firſt of all the Patriarchs who is mentioned to have vowed a Vow; as the moſt ancient <hi>Rabbi Abahu</hi> notes: <hi>Non dicitur, vovit forti</hi> Abraham, <hi>aut forti</hi> Iſaac, <hi>ſed forti</hi> Jacob, <hi>quod primus omnium vovit</hi> Jacob <hi>votum dicendo, &amp;c. Dicendo quid? Dicendo omnibus, ſeu docendo omnes, vovendum eſſe in Calamitatibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I think it a fine Dream of the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> who ſay,<note place="margin">Quam Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribilis eſt iſte Locu? erit Bethel; <hi>i. e.</hi> Domus Dei, ſeu Domus O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationis, (Dixit) Quandoqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem vidi hôc ipſo in loco aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum iri Templum. 2 Sam. 24.16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> is here mentioned, becauſe (in his ſleep) when he ſaw thoſe Degrees which reach'd Heaven, he had a Viſion of the Temple that <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> built; and being amazed at the Majeſty thereof, ſpeaks of it, and not of <hi>Bethel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>David</hi> (as they ſay) made the Vow, mentioned in this Pſalm, when the Plague was ſtayed at the Threſhing-Floor of the <hi>Jebuſite,</hi> and notice given him where the Temple ſhould be built, (as I have noted before.)</p>
               <p>Thus much may ſuffice by way of Argument, becauſe I have wrote more in Annotations upon this Pſalm, it being the longeſt and moſt difficult of my undertaking: Therefore I would be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the more Critical and Learned Reader, if the pains I took
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:199576:42"/>do neither pleaſe nor profit him in the full underſtanding, or explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſenſe hereof; becauſe theſe Notes were not intended to nauſeate the public with Crambes, but to inform thoſe, who are of as low rank in knowledge as my ſelf.</p>
               <p>Having put the word <hi>Shechinah</hi> in the Margin of my Verſes, I was once asked, why I did ſo? Therefore I here give the reaſon, becauſe I look on that Petition of the Pſalmiſt in the tenth Verſe, <hi>Janus</hi>-like, with two Faces, and moſt fit for <hi>Solomon</hi> to make, who built both the Temple, and a place, on purpoſe to worſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the holieſt of Holies, as if he had in this manner uttered his Mind.</p>
               <p>O! let me never prove ſo Idolatrous, as to turn away to other Gods, from this place of Worſhipping towards thy holy Temple (toward the <hi>Shechinah,</hi> the ſpecial place of thy Preſence,) nor let me prove ſo rejected by thee, as in thine Anger to be caſt out from before thee; but do thou impower me here to make thy Preſence, and to meet with thy Favours in my Worſhip and Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thee.</p>
               <p>Then I have doubly render'd the laſt Verſe, becauſe of the fulneſs of the Word <hi>(Induam),</hi> I'le cloath or put on, or throw on, as the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Retiarii</hi> did their Nets over the <hi>Secutores,</hi> i. e. pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly in the ſight of all Men, by covering and overwhelming them to diſgrace and deſtroy them.</p>
               <p>And this <hi>Induam</hi> is put in oppoſition to the cloathing of ſuch Men,<note place="margin">Verſ. 9, 10.</note> who having Truth and Righteouſneſs viſibly about them, (as it were, their Rayment) ſhall be manifeſtly preſerved and adorned thereby, as Judges by their Robes, through the over-ruling Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and Tuition of the Almighty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:199576:42"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord!<note place="margin">For <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> day, as it is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Church.</note> think on him whom thou didſt find, the Man ac╌cor╌ding to thy Mind; who could for thee with all things part: With his Wives love, and his own State, that on thy Ser╌vice he might wait. Remember <hi>Da╌vid</hi>'s humble Heart.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:199576:43"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Think on his Hand that brings thee Praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Strikes down thy Foes, ill Spirits lays,</l>
                  <l>And Gifts and Muſick doth afford:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.49 16.16</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though he did right,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.19. 6.16. 6.21.</note> he had much wrong,</l>
                  <l>Ev'n while he brought thy Ark along:</l>
                  <l>Remember <hi>David</hi>'s Troubles, Lord.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Think on the King, and on his Care,</l>
                  <l>Who for thy Place did well prepare;</l>
                  <l>Lord Bleſs his Heir,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 22.3. 4.5. 28.14 5. 2. 15.1.</note> build up his Houſe:</l>
                  <l>He would have ſet, and trimm'd up thine,</l>
                  <l>Lord! bleſs our acting his Deſign.</l>
                  <l>Remember <hi>David,</hi> and his Vows.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus ſaid he,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.9.</note> when he took his Oath,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Jacob</hi>'s God I plight my Troth,</l>
                  <l>Though I am ſafe in my new Forts:</l>
                  <l>I will not ſleep, nor there ſit ſtill,</l>
                  <l>'Till the Ark reſts on <hi>Zion</hi>'s Hill,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And from its<note n="*" place="margin">Tabernacula.</note> Curtains comes to<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſus eſt numero mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinis, ad plures Templi partes indicandas; nam in Templo (inquit <hi>Kimchi</hi>) crant Domus tres.</note> Courts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Houſe (though built) ſhall not be<note n="*" place="margin">It ſhall not be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated, and ſo not dwelt in 'till Conſecrated; as the <hi>Jews</hi> did ever ſome part of their Houſe for ſpecial Worſhip.</note> Bleſt;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.15, 16.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Bed ſhall yield me no more<note n="†" place="margin">Tandem tam longè abeſt ut ego ſim dormitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus; ut ne oculis quidem mictaturus ſim.</note> Reſt,</l>
                  <l>Than when 'twas ſearched for no good:</l>
                  <l>'Till here (with ours) God's Seat is found,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.5, 6.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Being with lofty Cedars crown'd,</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of <hi>Kiriath-jearim</hi>'s Wood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For in the Woods we lately found<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.1.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Joys, which to <hi>Abram</hi>'s Hill may ſound,</l>
                  <l>When God ſhall there be ſeen again;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.13. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.1. <hi>Mic.</hi> 5.2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>As firſt at <hi>Bethlem</hi> we did hear</l>
                  <l>How glorious all his Goings were,</l>
                  <l>Up to the Mountams from the Plain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And while God comes with the glad Throng,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 114.4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>In ev'ry place we hear this Song,</l>
                  <l>See, ſee, where our Beloved goes:</l>
                  <l>That he may ſtand on <hi>Sion</hi> ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Look how he leaps from Hill to Hill,</l>
                  <l>And makes us skip for joy, like Roes.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:199576:43"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>John.</hi> 2.22.</note> let's to <hi>Sion</hi> march along</l>
                  <l>In order, (leſt we Worſhip wrong)</l>
                  <l>After the Ark our Courſe is bent:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 10.33, 35, 36.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>We'll worſhip with the ſolemn Cries,</l>
                  <l>Riſe, Lord! unto thy Reſt ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Riſe to a Temple from a Tent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Train ſhall ſhout,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 15.27.</note> and ſo will I,</l>
                  <l>The Choir ſhall raiſe their Voices high;</l>
                  <l>The Prieſts ſhall ſhew the Sanctity</l>
                  <l>Both of thy Perſon, and their Place,</l>
                  <l>By being cloath'd with Righteouſneſs:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 6.12, 13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And thine Anointed thou ſhalt bleſs,</l>
                  <l>Nor from thy<note n="*" place="margin">Or <hi>Favour.</hi> See <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s Notes on the word.</note> Preſence turn his Face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh!<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.21.</note> never turn from us thy Face,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>David</hi>'s ſake, love <hi>David</hi>'s Race;</l>
                  <l>Do not his Stock (as <hi>Saul</hi>'s) diſown:</l>
                  <l>Since, if his Sons thy Laws obey,</l>
                  <l>Thou,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 9.17.</note> Lord, haſt ſworn his<note n="*" place="margin">De fructu Ventris tui, quoniam uterus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xoris cum omni ſuo fructu ad Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum pertinet.</note> Seed ſhall ſway,</l>
                  <l>And here for ever have a Throne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For here hath God his Favour ſhown,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.12.13.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And choſe our Dwellings for his own;</l>
                  <l>He will not ſtay with <hi>Edom</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Neither with <hi>Edom</hi> whom he hated; nor <hi>Obed Edom</hi> whom he bleſſed.</note> ſtill,</l>
                  <l>But his Proviſions ſhall bleſs ours,</l>
                  <l>Since on the Rich he dainty's ſhow'rs,</l>
                  <l>And can with Bread the Hungry fill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here will I ſit, ſaith God,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 6.41.</note> and Carve</l>
                  <l>To each poor Soul,<note place="margin">Significare vult apertam &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtam ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem quae omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus pateat, cum ſacerdotes ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te quaſi veſte circumdarentur; qui nunquam deerint gratia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum repetenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Officio.</note> that none may ſtarve;<note place="margin">Victum eis (non vidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am) benedicam.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>All Wants I will ſo far ſupply,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, as the 72 Interp. will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, which properly ſignifies <hi>Veniſon</hi> (a dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty indeed,) but it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies more largely any <hi>Victuals</hi> or <hi>Proviſions.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>That a large Alb of Thankfulneſs</l>
                  <l>Shall be my Prieſt's perpetual Dreſs,</l>
                  <l>And Saints ſhall ſet their Joys on high.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>On high ſhall <hi>David</hi> ſee my Love,</l>
                  <l>As here in <hi>Sion;</hi> ſo above,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod, ſhall bud his<note n="*" place="margin">His Royal Dignity, Power, and Off ſpring. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11.36.</note> Horn:</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, which myſtically re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to Chriſt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.2.</note>Glory's own Lamp lights up his Line,</l>
                  <l>And on his Head my Crown ſhall ſhine;</l>
                  <l>But on his Foes I'le<note n="‖" place="margin">Haud ſecus ac Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarii; ut ſupra in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:199576:44"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Glory be to the Father, Son,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Holy-Ghoſt, the Three in One,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whom as one Being we adore:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tho ev'ry Perſon of the Three</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For ever was, ſhall ever be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And is, God Bleſſed evermore.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:199576:44"/>
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Thirteenth <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXXII. PSALM.</head>
               <p>O Lord God! that thou mayeſt the more graciouſly conſider us and our Affairs, Remember our Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> we beſeech thee, and all his Afflictions, all his Humblings, all his Troubles, his Cares, and Loves, and Paſſions for us: look how through the whole Volume of thy Book it is written of him, That he ſhould fulfill thy Will, O God! and therefore he begger'd himſelf ſo far as to be born of the Stock and Lineage of <hi>David,</hi> that he might perform the Promiſe he had made, not to fail his People, but to become their Righteouſneſs, and their Redemption; and ſo though <hi>the Foxes had holes, and the Birds of the Air neſts, he would not have where to lay his Head:</hi> Neither would he give ſleep to his Eyes, but would be walking, and watching, and praying, whole Nights together, that he might be doing good to us, for us, in us, and with us, that here again in this baſe Earth and World of ours, he might find out an Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation for the Mighty God, and a place where his holy Dove might reſt. Grant then, O glorious Lord! that all his Labours and Deſires, his Endeavours and good Will concerning us may not be fruſtrated, but let us be built up a Spiritual Houſe upon him, and be bleſt in our Undertakings through him unto thy Glory; that as we have been directed, ſo we may go on (not ſtand ſtill) to ſee thy Salvation, and to worſhip thy Goodneſs, which doth ariſe with healing under its Wings for us, as a Hen, and as an Eagle, to cure, to carry, to ſecure and feed us, to make our Natures thy Abode, our Hearts thy San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, our Souls the reſting Place, both for thee, and the Ark of thy Strength; and all this, to what purpoſe? but for our Advantage, (not thine) that we might be a Choſen Generation, a Royal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, cloathed with Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, and cover'd with thy Comelineſs, which inveſts us with all Peace and Joy through the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>O therefore! let us lift up our Hearts with Love, and Praiſe, and Comfort, in believing, truſting, and begging, for thy Son's ſake, that neither our Faces may be turned from thee to go a Whoring after other things (that are not God, nor indeed good), nor let the face of thine Anointed be turned ſo away from us, as not to know us at the laſt Day.</p>
               <p>No, bleſſed Lord! grant us ſuch an intereſt in our dear Redeemer, as that we may have a Title to thy Favour, and be able to put thee in mind how thou haſt ſworn, and wilt not fail unto thy well-beloved Son, that of the Fruit of his Body thou wilt ſet upon the Throne, and haſt promiſed to all true Believers (his Servants,) that if they keep thy Covenant, they and their Children ſhall Reign with thee for
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:199576:45"/>ever, and find new cauſe of rejoycing in thee, who haſt choſen the Sons of Men for thy <hi>Zion,</hi> and deſired their enlarged Souls for thy reſtful Habitation, and chief Delight!</p>
               <p>But when ſhall we come to this Joy unſpeakable, and full of Glory? When we have with patience waited on thy good pleaſure, and not fainted in our expectation of thy faithfulneſs, then for certain we ſhall ſee thee, abundantly bleſſing and rewarding the ſmall Proviſions made here to ſerve thee withall, and thou wilt ſatisfie ſuch as <hi>hunger and thirſt</hi> after thy Kingdom with the Bread of Life, and with the Wells of Salvation, and they ſhall be array'd like thy Prieſts with Holineſs, and ſhine like Lamps in thy Preſence for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>HElp us, O Mighty God of <hi>Jacob!</hi> to ſing no Requiems to our Souls or Conditions here, 'till we have not only heard of thee with the hearing of the Ear, but hearkened unto thee with the attention of the Mind, and come unto thee with the obedience of the Will, finding out a place in our Affections and Underſtandings where thou mayeſt dwell, that thou mayeſt hereafter prepare a Manſion for us, even in thy Houſe, O Father!</p>
               <p>And with us be mindful of all Degrees amongſt us, from <hi>David</hi> upon the Throne, to <hi>Job</hi> upon the Dunghill; be good unto them in all their Cares, Vows, Prayers, Devotions, and Afflictions, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the multitude of thy moſt tender Mercies, and comfortable Promiſes: Let the King rejoyce in thy ſtrength, O Lord! and do thou make his Power to flouriſh, and his Righteouſneſs to bloſſom like the Rod of <hi>Aaron;</hi> ordain a luſtre of Honour and Happineſs for him and his Houſe for evermore; let not his Candle go out in obſcurity, nor quench the Light of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but let his Enemies be inveloped with diſgrace and diſappointments, and cloath thy Prieſts, and our Church of <hi>England,</hi> with Honour, Proſperity, and perfect Redemption, that the Horn of <hi>David</hi> may bud amongſt us, and the Power of Godlineſs ſhoot forth every where in our Land, in the great City, in Princes Courts, and in thy Houſe and ours, ſo that thou mayeſt have Mercy on <hi>Zion,</hi> and repair the breaches of thy <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> while ſhe that ſate Diſconſolate as a Widow may now be feaſted with Bread from Heaven, with the <hi>Manna</hi> of Divine Ordinances duly adminiſtred; ſo that no Soul amongſt us may go empty away, but that even he who gathers leaſt may have no lack.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.18.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Lord! thou canſt make thy holy Viands, like <hi>David</hi>'s Proviſion at the Paſſover, be dealt ſo plentifully to every one, as that none ſhall be unprovided for, or aſhamed, who depend like <hi>Ruth</hi> upon thy Bounty; but they who deſpiſe thee ſhall be wrapt up in Confuſion as in a Cloak</p>
               <p>Therefore let thy Servants joy in thy Salvation, and all our People know the Lord, acknowledging his Goodneſs and his Bounty that bleſſes the Abundance of the Rich, and fills the Hungry with good things, that both may have Bread enough, and neither want nor repine, but ſeek their Food of God, while he makes thoſe that depart wickedly from him to continue in ſhame and ſcarcity.</p>
               <p>Ah! that we may ſtand in a we and not ſin, leſt we inherit the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of Fools, inſtead of the Kingdom and Crown of <hi>David;</hi> ſo provide for us, gracious Maſter, in every ſtate and condition, as may ſeem beſt to thy God-like Wiſdom, and prove moſt to thine Eternal Glory, if not to ours, O! <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:199576:45"/>
            <head>THE FOURTEENTH Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXXXIII. <hi>PSALM,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Was compoſed by <hi>David</hi> (as ſome think) at his Coronation,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 5. 1 Chr. 1. 2 Pet. 1.7. 1 Sam. 17.29. 1 Sam. 18. 2 Sam. 1. 2 Sam. 3. 2 Sam. 10. &amp; 9. &amp; 18. &amp;c.</note> after his eight years Civil War, to exhort the People to Love and Amity, according to the exhortation of the Apoſtle, for thoſe were the Graces which did moſt adorn his Life, both when a public and a private Perſon; and ſo this Pſahn, as the next, was fitted for the moſt Solemn Times of Worſhip, and the happy Return from Bondage and Captivity, becauſe it magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the pious Accord, Uniformity, and Bleſſed Communion of the Church of God in all Times.</p>
               <p>It Celebrates the Excellencies of Love, both in and towards God and Man; it reflects much Joy from the Conſideration of the Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Union between Chriſt and his Members, whom he owns as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who ſhall live, and live together alſo with him, though he is their High Prieſt, Rock, and Prince, according to the moſt apt Compariſons of the holy Oyl, and high-born Dew; which Similies,<note place="margin">In <hi>Zoroba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua,</hi> Types of the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah.</hi>
                  </note> as well as the Subject, were ſo well calculated to the Time, when there was a Prince and an High Prieſt reſtored again to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that it is no wonder we find it placed among the Graduals.</p>
               <p>Some apply it to all the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Love one towards another, who were Brethren of the ſame Stock (as we are all in <hi>Adam;</hi>) and likewiſe to their Love of their Ruler, who was higher than the reſt, (as was ſhewn in <hi>Saul</hi>) like Mount <hi>Hermon</hi> and <hi>Sion,</hi> more advancing than other Hills: Therefore to animate us with the like affections towards our Brethren, Parents, and Superiours, they ſay, the Prieſt's Bleſſing is compared to the Sacred Oyl, and the Prince's Favour to the fruitful Dew, (according to that expreſſion of the Wiſeſt of Kings) which deſcends from the higheſt to the loweſt, and is both pleaſant and profitable to all;<note place="margin">Prov. 19.12.</note> as the Heathen Poet <hi>Meander</hi> (once quoted by St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf) could ſay,</p>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:199576:46"/>
               <p>Some of the <hi>Rabbins</hi> think it a particular Eulogy of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and Conformity among the Prieſts in their Religious Exerciſes; and therefore mention is made of <hi>Aaron</hi> the <hi>moſt Anointed</hi> of the Lord (as he may be termed, rather than <hi>chief Anointed,</hi>) becauſe moſt Oyl was expended on him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E╌hold how plea╌ſant 'tis!<note place="margin">For Saint <hi>George</hi>'s, or <hi>All-Saints</hi> Day.</note> how good! But, O! how rare, and hard to find, Brethren, of the ſame Houſe and Blood, be╌come of the ſame way and mind.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:199576:46"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Honey, ſtrong and ſweet,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Judg.</hi> 14.14.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Tis thus to ſee Men's Hearts and Hands,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s and <hi>David</hi>'s meet,</l>
                  <l>Twiſting together in Love's Bands.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.3.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When Prince and People ſo are one,</l>
                  <l>As that the Oyl, pour'd on his Head,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.39. 5.3. 19.23.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Down to the loweſt Limb doth run;</l>
                  <l>In Grace, and Peace, and Pardon ſpread.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis like the precious Ointment ſhed<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Levit.</hi> 8.12.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Upon the High Prieſt's hallow'd Crown,</l>
                  <l>Which both perfum'd his Beard and Head,</l>
                  <l>And thence upon his Clothes fell down.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus have I ſeen Clouds big with Rain</l>
                  <l>Firſt give their Dews to all the Hills,</l>
                  <l>And then ſhow'r Wealth on the low Plain</l>
                  <l>As Friendſhip benefits diſtills.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>On Friendſhip's Fleece God's Love brings down<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Judg.</hi> 6.38, 39.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Bleſſings, as numberleſs as Drops;</l>
                  <l>Which from Mount <hi>Sion</hi> deck the Town,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide</hi> Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And cloath the Fields from <hi>Hermon</hi>'s Tops.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As to the Vale, theſe Mountains are;</l>
                  <l>So to the Weak, the Potent prove</l>
                  <l>Uſeful and kind, though diſtant far;</l>
                  <l>Yet center'd, like the World, by Love.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For all our Comforts come from Love,</l>
                  <l>By Love, God gives the Happy Life;</l>
                  <l>That Bleſt below, and beſt above,</l>
                  <l>There without end, here without ſtrife.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:199576:47"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Glory to him who makes our Bliſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To the one God, in Perſons three;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As in beginning was, now is,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſhall be to Eternity.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:199576:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Fourteenth <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXXIII. PSALM.</head>
               <p>O Bleſſed Father! who haſt made many of us of one Blood and Kind: O bleſſed Saviour! who haſt made us many of one Bread, and one Lump: O bleſſed Spirit! who art the Love, both of the Father, and of the Son, ſhed this abroad into all our Hearts abundantly; look upon us graciouſly, O thou only one, moſt loving and pitying Lord God! that we may look upon thee better (though it be but darkly at the beſt) in that Sea of Glaſs before the Throne, in that cleareſt mirror and reflection of thy favour to Mankind, to wit, in Chriſt incarnate, in whom God is moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully, wiſely, and kindly ſeen to reconcile the World (what is that but Vileneſs, Vanity, and Vexation, Frailty, and a Curſe) unto himſelf, that Man might be far more able than he was by the Glaſſes and Laver of the Tabernacle, both to ſee his Spots and Pollutions to get clean from them, and that God might be conſider'd and admired not ſo much in the broken Glaſs of Nature, nor in the blotted Book of the Creature, (which ſhew us his power and greatneſs) as in the Face of a Redeemer, in the Teſtament of the holy <hi>Jeſus,</hi> which moſt plainly, and yet moſt gloriouſly ſpeaks thy Love and Goodneſs, and calls for ours; ſince if thou haſt ſo loved this naughty World, and us that help to make it worſe, how ought we to love thee, and alſo to love one another?</p>
               <p>O how good, as well as how pleaſant, a thing it is to know <hi>Chriſt</hi> as our Head, and we our ſelves his Members! This is as ſweet and uſeful as Life it ſelf, to make our ſhort Lives here not tedious to our ſelves or others; nay, this is <hi>Life Eternal,</hi> becauſe Charity never fails: We ſhall have that Grace for all if we are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> we ſhall keep it always if we are Saints, for it is Holineſs, and will be Happineſs; it is the Oyl that from our Head, from our everlaſting <hi>Aaron,</hi> falls down to the very Skirts of his Clothing, to revive and refreſh the loweſt and moſt humbled Sinner (if believing), and it is that Anointing from above which we muſt not want, eſpecially at the laſt Article of Life, in the greateſt extremities of Temptation, but we muſt carry it along with us into our Father's preſence; then ſhall we be in his ſight as a Field which the Lord hath bleſt, then will he ſmell the Odour of our elder Brother's Veſt upon us, and we ſhall inherit the Promiſes, and abide in his Love in the participation, and in the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation thereof, Divine Love being the Dew of Heaven that cauſes the fruitfulneſs of the Earth; it makes us high and white like <hi>Hermon,</hi> pleaſant and ſafe as Mount <hi>Sion;</hi> it makes our Superiours, and the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:199576:48"/>great ones of the Earth, not to be Rocks of Offence to us, but to be rather, as the ſhadows of a Rock in a dry Land, needful Supports, convenient Sanctuaries and Refreſhments, and it cauſes God to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a Bleſſing on us from all degrees of People above us, and of conditions round about us. Therefore,</p>
               <p>Dear Lord! help us to live in ſuch Concord and brotherly Kindneſs, as that we may be Bleſſed from all our Relations, from our Superiours, by having the Oyl of Spiritual Bleſſings, and the Dew of Temporal Favours beſtowed on us, Love and good Will from Equals, Prayers and good Wiſhes from Inferiours; being ſo careful and affectionate, both for thy Prieſts, and for our Princes, as that neither <hi>Moſes</hi> nor <hi>Aaron</hi> may be murmured at, but obeyed by us, and we may be prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and guided by their Hands in the Spirit and Practice of all true Love and Charity, for the honour of our Chriſtian Profeſſion, and for the glory of thy holieſt Name, O <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> our Lord! who liveſt and reigneſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:199576:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE FIFTEENTH Pſalm of Degrees, BEING The CXXXIV. <hi>PSALM,</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>Was compoſed by <hi>David</hi> (<hi>De Muys</hi> thinks) as well as the former, and appointed to put the People in mind of their more ſolemn Times of Meeting with that pious, charitable, and unſpotted Souls, with which they ought to approach God; this being an Euge, an incitement to all, who are the Lord's Servants, to be conſtant and pure in his Service, as a particular <hi>hoc age</hi> to the Prieſts at the Canonical Hours of Prayer, and ſtated Times of public Worſhip, to lift up clean Hands, and holy Hearts.</p>
               <p>It is a proper Cloſe to the preceding Hymns, being often ſung at Midnight at the end of the Nocturnal Offices by the <hi>Jews,</hi> and deſign'd by me for the Eves of our greater Feſtivals: It is an Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation generally directed not only to the Prieſts, who kept the Watch in the Temple, ſo to the People, who watched these Days and Nights, for many departed not, as you may gather from <hi>Pſal. 92.2.</hi> and <hi>Luke 2.37.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſeems to me moſt probable, that this Pſalm was compoſed by <hi>Ezra</hi> the Prieſt, or ſome of his Time, not only becauſe it is the laſt of the Graduals, which were accommodated for the Return from Captivity, but becauſe it is Dramatic; chiefly concerning the Prieſts, who ſtand by night in the Houſe of the Lord; or as the <hi>72d</hi>, in the Courts of the Houſe, which was not built in <hi>David</hi>'s time; and therefore it is not ſo likely a compoſition of <hi>David</hi>'s, but of <hi>Ezra,</hi> when the holy manner of worſhipping God was reſtored, <hi>Ezra 8.6.</hi> and the Prieſts ſet in their Courſes, <hi>Verſ. 7.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt Verſe of this Pſalm I ſhould ſuppoſe the Choir joyning to the Muſic, and then the Chief Prieſt (for that Watch) giving the reſt Directions as in the ſecond Verſe, and they again in the third Verſe bleſſing him, (for it is <hi>Bleſs thee,</hi> and not <hi>yee</hi>) though in my verſion I uſe the Plural throughout.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:199576:49"/>
            </div>
            <div type="metrical_Psalm">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL ye,<note place="margin">A <hi>Nocturnis</hi> for <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Eve.</note> who God's Do╌me╌ſtics are, ſee you, with An╌gels wait; and in your Courſes, like each Star, by Night ſhine at Heav'ns Gate.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Look while ye ſtand,<note place="margin">Among the <hi>Jews</hi> the Choir ſtood, the People kneeled, the High-Prieſt ſate, and the waſhings of their Hands and Feet (ſo frequent during the time of their officiating) were call'd <hi>Sanctifications.</hi>
                     </note> or kneel, or ſit,</l>
                  <l>Ye ſerve and bleſs the Lord;</l>
                  <l>Look that your Hands God's Altar fit,</l>
                  <l>And to his Praiſe accord.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Look ye be clean, for Holineſs</l>
                  <l>Becomes God's holy Place;</l>
                  <l>Watch well,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, in the 72. is ſhort of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, though it means in holy Things, as well as Places, for it ſignifies <hi>Holineſs</hi> in the Abſtract (<hi>Chriſt</hi> typified by the Ark of the Covenant); and ſuch Holineſs in Men as could adapt them for the diſcharge of their Duty, which is hinted by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8. And this was ſignified by the <hi>Jews</hi> often waſhing their Hands and Feet before their Praying, which was ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Sanctification: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t alibi indigitavi.</hi>
                     </note> and Pray, that Filthineſs</l>
                  <l>None of God's Works deface.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then God, who made the World, and ſtays</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Sion,</hi> Grace ſhall ſend;</l>
                  <l>'Till he ſhall Bleſs, and we ſhall Praiſe,</l>
                  <l>From hence, World without end.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:199576:49"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>Gloria Patri, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To God the Father, God the Son,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And God the Holy-Ghoſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Be Glory giv'n, by ev'ry one</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who make the Lord their Boaſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:199576:50"/>
               <head>CONTEMPLATIONS and COLLECTS ON THE Fifteenth <hi>PSALM</hi> of <hi>DEGREES,</hi> BEING The CXXXIV. PSALM.</head>
               <p>O Thou that accepteſt not the Perſons of Princes, nor regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt the Rich more than the Poor, ſince they are all alike the Works of thy Hands! grant that we may not be ſuch Fools as to forget thee in any time of our quiet, fulneſs, or repoſe, leſt thou come at an Hour when thou art not look'd for by us, and find us unfit for thy Appearance, who canſt trouble whole Nations even at Midnight (at a time when we leaſt think of Diſturbance or Remove), as we have great Examples in the People of <hi>Iſrael, Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Aſſyria;</hi> for there is not any Darkneſs (no not the ſhadows of Death) where the workers of Iniquity can hide themſelves from thine Eyes, though all the Mountains of the World ſhould cover them; thou beholdeſt all our Goings, though thy Foot-ſteps are too little regarded by us.</p>
               <p>Therefore let us not think to do miſchief or wrong like the Evil one, who ſowed Tares while other Men ſlept; nor to commit Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or Robbery;<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 3.20.</note> nor to Defraud or Deceive, like the <hi>Harlot</hi> at Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night; but even at that Seaſon be Chaſt, and Pious, and Charitable, like <hi>Boaz,</hi> denying our ſelves, and maſtering our Concupiſcences, and (like <hi>Sampſon</hi> in <hi>Gaza</hi>) diſappoint the malice of that implacable Adverſary, who hunts after our Souls, and ceaſes not, like a Dog, to go about <hi>ſeeking whom he may devour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord! deliver thou my Darling from his Power, as thou didſt St. <hi>Paul,</hi> even at ſuch a diſmal time when I may ſeem in his very Jaws; then let my Soul eſcape and get away, and find a way to ſerve thee, (as that choſen Veſſel did) who could Pray and ſing Praiſes unto thee even at Midnight; ſo let us endeavour to worſhip the Lord with holy Worſhip, with clean Hands, and a pure Heart, that we may ſtand on his holy Hill, and remember in all the Formalities of outward Cleanneſs to keep our Spirits pure; and in all our Approaches to thee, to keep our ſelves unſpotted of the World; to this end give us inward Holineſs, and the Sanctifications both of Heart and Life, that in the darkeſt hour of Temptation, in the deadeſt time of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, in the cloudieſt night of Trouble, or of Agonies, we may lift up our Praiſes and Adorations unto thee, who canſt ſend thine Angel (as thou didſt once thy Son, at ſuch a time) to comfort and recover our vile Natures, and to command Deliverances unto thy People, even from thy moſt holy Place.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:199576:50"/>
               <p>O! that we may be of the number of thoſe who qualifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by thy Service for the better diſcharge of their Duty and thy Will; that having the filthy Garments of our own evil Thoughts, Words, and Actions (like <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s the High-Prieſt's) taken off from us, we may not have <hi>Satan</hi> left at our right Hands to accuſe or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand us, but may ſee <hi>Jeſus</hi> at thy right Hand interceding for us; and being cloathed in the long Robes of his Righteouſneſs, we may lift up our Hands in thy Sanctuary, and bleſs thee for evermore, who haſt made the Heavens as well as the Sea, for thy Children to adore thee in, O!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:199576:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE FIFTEEN Pſalms of Degrees, OR ASCENTS,</head>
            <p>Are ſo called, becauſe they were ſung Anthem-wiſe by ſeveral Parts of the Choir, with Elevation of Voice on ſome higher Ground, or place of advantage; perhaps on the Steps of the Temple, which in <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Viſion are mentioned to be Fifteen in number:<note place="margin">Ca. 40. v. 22.34.</note> And juſt ſo many Stairs, ſay the <hi>Talmudiſts,</hi> were there mounting from the Women's Court to the Men's, on which, they fancy, theſe <hi>PSALMS</hi> were ſung, and therefore thus termed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Symachus.</hi>)</p>
            <p>But I think rather becauſe they were much uſed by the <hi>Hebrews</hi> upon their coming up from <hi>Babylon,</hi> and at the building of the ſecond Temple,<note place="margin">Cap. 8.</note> as may be gueſſed from <hi>Nehemiah;</hi> at which time they might indeed begin very properly with the <hi>120th</hi> Pſalm, by reaſon of the contempt and calumniation of their ill-willers at that time; who were ſuch as are there deſcribed <hi>Arabians,</hi> crafty and cruel Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, who maliciouſly oppoſed both their unlooſing the Chains of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, and the erection of their Buildings.</p>
            <p>Need was there then of Songs of E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ation and Aſcents to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance God's high Deliverances of them, and exalt his Praiſe and Glory in the moſt excellent way of rejoycing, which was in their emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Muſic, as the Title <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, rendered <hi>Cantica Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatum,</hi> may likewiſe bear.</p>
            <p>As alſo to revive their drooping Spirits by ſome pleaſant kind of Melody or lofty Note, well known to the <hi>Jews</hi> by the name of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſome ſuppoſe may here import no more than this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the front of other Pſalms, <hi>viz.</hi> to notifie that the Tune or Key theſe were to be ſang in, was the ſame with ſuch other Pſalms as were known to begin with the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:199576:51"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
